Hmmm.
Mhmm.
Music
Music
All right,
All right,
join me and clear the thank you for the
join me and clear the thank you for the
Introduce Academia Sinica to participate
介紹中央研究院來參加
Our presentation for today's Feast of Knowledge
我們今天的知識饗宴的演講
I'm here to represent the Central Court
我在這邊要來代表中央院
Introducing our speakers today
介紹我們今天的講者
Today's speaker is Professor Cai Dingping
今天的主講人是蔡定平教授
Currently in Academia Sinica
現在現任中研院
Director of Applied Science Research Center
應用科學研究中心的主任
Special Review Researcher
跟特評研究員
He is also a special commentary professor at the Department of Physics, National Taiwan University
他也是臺灣大學物理系的特評教授
Some of the information you have is very detailed.
大家手上的有些資料都有很詳細的
Introduction to Professor Cai
對蔡教授的介紹
I just need to pick a few points
我只要挑幾個重點
He is now the chairman of the Taiwan Information Storage Association
他現在是臺灣資訊儲存協會的理事長
Chairman of the Optoelectronic Society of the Republic of China
中華民國光電學會理事長
It is also a meeting of the American Physical Society in Taiwan
也是臺灣也是美國物理學會的會事
Meetings of the International Society for Electrical and Electronic Engineering
國際電子電機工程學會的會事
Meetings of the Optical Society of America
美國光學學會的會事
International Optoelectronic Society
國際光電學會
Meetings of the Society of Engineering
工程學會的會事
Meeting of the Academy of Electromagnetic Sciences
電磁科學院會事
There is also a meeting of the Asia Pacific Academy of Materials Sciences
還有亞太材料科學院會事
And finally, the meeting of the Physical Society of the Republic of China
然後最後是中華民國物理學會的會事
So his academic achievement is very high
所以他在學術上的成就非常高
Then published more than two hundred papers
然後發表了非常兩百多篇的論文
book or other that chapter
專書或其他的那個章節
A total of forty-nine conference papers
會議論文共有四十九篇
Thirty-nine other technical reports and other papers
其他技術報告跟其他的論文三十九篇
There are 41 domestic and foreign patents
有四十一個國內外的專利
So the academic achievement is very high
所以學術上的成就非常高
has won many awards
曾經得過非常多的獎項
I just cite a few of the most important ones
我只舉幾個最重要的就是
National Science Council's Fifty Scientific Achievement Awards
國科會的五十科學成就獎
There is also the Industry-University Cooperation Award from the Ministry of Education
還有教育部的產學合作獎
the main thing is
最主要的是
NSC Contact Research Award twice
國科會的接觸研究獎兩次
and academic awards from the Ministry of Education
還有教育部的學術獎
it's very rare
這是非常難得的
Foundation Research Contact Awards and more
基金會研究接觸獎等等
The topic he is talking to us today is
那今天他在跟我們講的題目是
Very relevant to his research is the
跟他的研究非常相關的是關於
About Photon New Era
關於光子新紀元
because we know that in 2015
因為我們知道2015年
Last year was an International Year of Light
去年是一個國際光之年
Specially designate this year as the Year of Light
特別把這一年定為光之年
It's because I want to attract everyone
是因為想要引起大家
Focus on so-called photonics
關注所謂的光子學
light-based technology
還以光為基礎的科技
in this new era
在這個新的紀元
In this new century of ours
在這個我們新的這個世紀裡面
Lots of new camp fun going on
所進行的很多新營有趣
useful some development
有用的一些發展
This is the topic he mainly introduced to us today.
這是他今天主要給我們介紹的題目
Chinese is called Photon New Era
中文叫做光子新紀元
English is Photonics for the New Era
英文是Photonics for the New Era
So I thought my introduction
所以我想我的介紹
not too long
不要太長
everyone can save time
大家可以把時間留下來
Let's listen to Director Cai's wonderful speech
我們聽聽蔡主任非常精采的演講
thank you all we have now applauded
謝謝大家 我們現已熱烈掌聲
welcome to our chair today
歡迎我們今天的主席
good night everybody
各位晚安
It is a great honor to have this opportunity today
今天非常榮幸有這個機會
Come to this today's
來參加今天的這個
very important report
很重要的一個報告
I will give you a brief report
跟各位做一個簡單的報告
Thanks also to my colleagues
也很感謝我的同仁
they helped me choose
他們幫我選了
Fortunix for the New Era
Fortunix for the New Era
title of this speech
這個演講的title
I feel very honored
我覺得是非常榮幸
in the first chamber of the house of representatives
在眾議院第一次院內
inside give such a report
裡面給這樣一個報告
Coming to the House of Representatives is already fast
來眾議院已經很快的
just over four years passed
就四年多過去
Learned a lot in the past four years
在過去這四年多學習到很多
There are many very, very good and outstanding seniors, experts and scholars in the Chinese language
中文語言有很多位非常非常優秀跟卓越的前輩跟專家學者
so if there's anything wrong with my report today
所以如果我今天的報告有什麼不對的地方
Ken please correct me a lot
肯請大家多多指正
Then my report today is roughly divided into two parts.
那我今天的報告大概分成兩部分
In the first part, let me briefly tell you
第一部分先跟各位簡單的講一下
A short story about the 2015 International Year of Light in Taiwan
2015年國際光之年在台灣的這個簡短的一個故事
about ten minutes
大概花十幾分鐘
Then I will report to you some recent stories about optics
然後再跟各位報告就是光學最近的一些小故事
That's because a colleague specifically told me
那因為同仁特別跟我講說
This talk is not an academic talk is this knowledge sharing
這個演講不是學術演講是這個知識分享
So it must be maintained without the formula
所以必須要維持在沒有公式
then tell the story
然後要講故事
This is very difficult for me
這對我來講是非常不容易的一件事
because you cut pork every day
因為你每天都在切豬肉
Suddenly today came a handful of vegetables for you to cut
突然今天來了一把菜讓你切
that's weird
那就是覺得很奇怪
So I started preparing for this talk this morning
所以我從今天早上開始準備這個talk
ready to just
準備到剛剛
so sorry
所以很抱歉
If there is something incomplete, please advise
如果有不周全的地方請多多指教
The Year of Light 2015
2015年的光之年
Basically because of the past few years
基本上因為這幾年
I have been back to Taiwan for more than 20 years
我回到台灣20幾年
this continuous learning
這個不斷的學習
continuous efforts
不斷的努力
I have always believed that science is the way of the old country
一直認為說科學是舊國之道
It is also the way of the new country
也是新國之道
but over the years
但是這些年來
Not only are there things in the courtyard
不僅是院內有一些事情
There are many other foreign things outside the hospital
院外也很多其他國外的事情
On the contrary, many important things
反而是很多重要的事情
That's why I want to say that I still use such precious time
所以我才想說我還是用這麼寶貴的時間
Tell everyone the ins and outs of this whole story
跟各位報告這整件故事的來龍去脈
Because a lot of people don't know
因為真的非常多的人並不清楚
But in fact, this is a very large event that takes place around the world.
但其實這是一件非常大的在全球上都有的活動
First of all, I would like to thank Chen Boru, a student from Jiangdong University
首先要感謝江東大學陳柏如同學
There is also a dub that puts this
還有一段配音是把這個
A short video of a whole world to share with you
一個全球的一個短片跟大家一起分享
thank you all
謝謝大家
Light allows us to see what Chie Yue imagined
光讓我們看見千越想像的事
Light will drive the economy of the future
光將帶動未來的經濟
Light enables us to reduce disease and treat disease
光使我們能減少疾病治療疾病
Light guards our society
光守護著我們的社會
Light will be the key to solving the most expensive problems of the mind
光將會成為解決心理上最極貴問題的關鍵
When the light fades and disappears on Dali
當光漸減消失在大理上
our day will be over
我們的一天也將結束
And our future will shine and keep turning
而我們的未來將會光而繼續轉動
Thanks
謝謝
last shot elected one
最後一個鏡頭當選了一個
The last shot was actually selected as an image of a very important promotion in the world
最後一個鏡頭事實上當選了一個全球的一個很重要的一個宣傳的一個影像
That image is a little girl
那個影像就是一個小女生
Not just now that girl has a picture
不是剛剛那位女生有一張照片
is a little girl
是一個小女生
lying on a wooden floor
趴在一個木質的地板上面
Then there is an LED light that costs less than one dollar next to it
然後旁邊有一個不到一美金的LED的燈
that was in south america
那是在南美洲
a very poor remote country
一個非常貧窮的偏遠的鄉下
places without electricity
沒有電力設施的地方
children in
小朋友在
afternoon
下午
After assisting parents Luo Blind
協助父母親羅盲之後
back home
回到家中
Then use the Une
然後用聯合國文教組織
LED light provided
所贈送的LED的燈
lying on the floor to write his day's
趴在地板上寫他當日的
home work
家庭作業
those are
那些都是
united nations humanitarian organization
聯合國人道組織
The United Nations Culture and Education is the institution of UNEASYS
聯合國文教這個就是UNEASYS的這個機構
to help remote countries
去協助偏遠的國家
In fact, in 2013, this activity has already been promoted by Promote
那事實上2013年這個活動就已經開始被Promote
That's when UNESCO declared 2015 to be the International Year of Light
那是由聯合國教科文組織宣佈2015年變成是國際光之年
So why the International Year of Light?
那為什麼要國際光之年?
Because in fact in 2005
因為其實2005年
Do you still remember the year when Building 101 was just completed?
各位還記得在101大樓剛剛蓋好的那一年
None of his offices are rented out
他的辦公室都沒有租出去
Then the window later has an E equal to MC squared
然後窗戶後來就有一個E等於MC平方
Celebrating the Year of Physics
慶祝物理年
2015 is the year of light
那2015年就是光之年
There is also a chemical year and an astronomical year in between
中間還有化學年 天文年
why?
那為什麼?
The reason, of course, is that light is a very important
原因當然是因為光是一個非常重要的
is an important element of human civilization
是人類文明的重要的一個元素
an important element in the origin of life
也是生命起源的一個重要的元素
Arguments are currently important in medicine, communication, economy, environment, society, and culture
論事目前在醫療、通訊、經濟、環境、社會、文化上都非常重要
So it was decided to have a light year
所以決定要有一個光之年
85 UNESCO members from all over the world participated
全球有85個聯合國教科文組織會員參加
Although we are not, we in Taiwan also participated in this event
雖然我們不是,但是我們台灣也參加了這個活動
This event is a global event
這個活動是一個全球性的活動
Why do you want to promote this matter?
為什麼要去Promote這件事情?
It is because human civilization, whether in science and technology, or in nature and culture
是因為人類文明不論是在科學技術、還有自然和文化上面
Light actually played a very important role.
光其實是扮演了非常重要的一個角色
Needless to say, many people know about this
不用質疑的,很多的人都知道這件事情
but ignored it
但是卻忽略了它
Because Laozi said that elephants have no form
因為老子說大象無形
It's just that many people take it granted
就是很多人take it granted
That is to say, take it for granted, as if the light turns on when you press your hand
就是說認為理所當然好像就是手一按燈就亮了
Well, a lot of things are not like that
那其實很多事情並非如此
in many places around the world
在很多全球很多的地方
Human civilization still has a different aspect
人類的文明還是有不同樣的一個面向的
This year of light has a LOGO
這個光之年有一個LOGO
It is the light source representing the sun
就是代表太陽的光源
origin perpetual culture very long
起源 永續 文化 很長
There are also representatives of various international countries and races
還有代表各個國際 國家 種族
There is also a sense of tolerance
也還有包容的意識
Then different colors represent different races
然後不同的顏色代表不同的種族
Spectrum also represents the diversity of science, art, culture, education, etc.
光譜 還有代表科學 藝術 文化 教育等多元化
Diversified one LOGO
多樣化的一個LOGO
I have prepared ten badges for each
我這邊有準備了各十個徽章
I'll send it to you later
等一下要送給各位
There are two kinds here, there are twenty
這邊有兩種 有二十個
One is the badge made by the International Society for Optoelectronic Engineering
一個是國際光電工程學會做的徽章
The other one is Taiwan Fotonic Society
另外一個是台灣Fotonic Society
made badge
做的徽章
that was made by
那是由
Vice Chairman Sun Qingcheng designed it
孫慶成副理事長他設計的
There is a jade mountain at the bottom
底下還有一個玉山
Then the above LOGO is exactly the same
然後上面的LOGO完全一樣
Wait a minute, if you are interested, you can come and get it
等一下如果有興趣的可以來前面拿
In addition to that
另外就是說
Why choose 2015
為什麼選2015年
The reason is because of many important developments
原因是因為很多重要的一些發展
like this 1965 50 years ago
像這個1965年50年前
Gao Kun and the others developed this optical fiber technology
高坤他們發展了這個光纖的技術
then 1915
然後1915年
special relativity
狹義相對論
general relativity
廣義相對論
Estan's general theory of relativity
埃斯坦提出了廣義相對論
then 1865
然後1865年
Just happens to be Max Ware
就剛剛好是Max Ware
He took all the physical properties of this light
他把這個光的所有物理的特性
explained in terms of electromagnetic waves
用電磁波的方式來解釋
that 1815
那1815年
Fernand believes that light has the property of fluctuations
Fernand認定光是具有波動的性質
And then, 2015 is the year Western Civilization decides for the first time that humans understand what light is
然後呢,2015年是西方文明認定人類第一次了解什麼是光
There is the first book on light
有第一本光方面的書出來
What about this one haytham , an arab
那這個一本海塞姆呢,是一個阿拉伯人
He was originally an intellectual, working for the Emperor
他原來就是一個知識分子,為Emperor工作
Then, later, he was imprisoned in prison for minor incidents
然後呢,後來因為小的事情被囚禁在監獄中
He is in prison, there is nothing to do
他在監獄裡面呢,就沒有事情可以做
Because I am usually very busy, I have to prepare Powerpoint and speeches
因為平常非常忙,要準備Powerpoint,要準備演講
There's nothing to do in prison
那關在牢裡面沒有事情做
He began to notice that from sunrise to sunset, he looked at the fence of the cell
他就開始發現到說日起日落,然後看著牢房的這個柵欄
He discovered that light is a diameter, and then the shadow of light is like a straight line
他發現光是直徑的,然後光的影子是像一條直線一樣
So, he wrote down some very basic principles of optics
所以呢,他就寫下了一些很基本的光學原理
For example, say light is of diameter
例如說光是直徑的
The angle of this projection of light is relevant
光的這個投影的角度是相關的
He wrote some very basic concepts of geometric optics
他寫了一些很基本的幾何光學的一些概念
The origin of books that were then identified as optics by Western civilization
然後被西方文明認定是光學的書籍的起源
But here are Mozi, Shenggua and Li Shizhen
但是這邊有墨子、省瓜跟李時珍
In fact, Mozi was 2500 years ago
事實上在墨子也就是2500年前
This one specifically writes some very important descriptions of optics.
這個就特別寫了一些非常重要的一些光學的描述
That was also 3000 years ago in this year 1945
那也在3000年前在這個1945年
This in this 1945 in this prince's tomb in this Shanmen Gorge
這個在這個1945年在這個在這個山門峽的這個太子墓中
This is the discovery of the Western State's foreign tax
這個是發現了西州的洋稅
That foreign tax is one
那洋稅就是一個
This concave copper mirror
這種凹面的銅鏡
It can actually be used to dry some
它事實上就可以拿來把一些乾的
love grass or dried leaves
愛草或者是乾的樹葉
can be ignited
就可以引燃
It's kind of like a lighter now
有點像現在的打火機
that is to pick up
那就是拿起來
Beat Lai and smoke a cigarette
把賴打一打就抽個煙
or some incense
或點個香
Then this is such a thing
那這個是這樣一個東西
and it's done really well
而且它做得非常好
very well done
做得非常好
So the rep said
所以代表說
These technologies have actually been around for a long time.
這些技術事實上老早就存在了
Then in Needham's history of Chinese science and technology
然後李約瑟的中國科技史裡面
I mentioned Mozi about
就提到莫子關於
Optics Research Vs
光學的研究比
known greece as early as
所知的希臘為早
earlier than India and Arabia
比印度跟阿拉伯更早
Because Mozi was from 2500 years ago
因為莫子是2500年前的人
So in Mokin he has drawings
所以在莫金裡面他就有繪圖
that picture means
那個圖就是說
through a small hole
經過一個小孔
This image is upside down
這個成像是倒立的
That's all evidence
那這個都是有證據的
not made up
不是憑空捏造的
so here
所以這裡面
include
包括
Imaging with pinholes, including concave-convex mirror imaging
有小孔成像,包括凹凸面鏡的成像
Imaging including combined mirrors
包括組合面鏡的成像
In fact, two or three thousand years ago
事實上在兩三千年前
Humans have probably recorded
人類大概都已經有記載
and know these things
而且都知道這些事情
that's a pity
那很可惜的
That is to say, the optics textbooks we read
就是說我們讀的光學的課本
I study optics
我是學光學的
so no mention of these things
所以都沒有提到這些事情
do not know either
也不知道
Now everyone thinks that this optical
那現在大家認為說這個光學
The very important reason is because
非常重要的原因是因為
it is the origin of life
它是生命的起源
It is more important to keep in good health than everyone now
它跟現在大家都比較重視養生
Very related to this Healthcare
跟這個Healthcare非常有關係
and everyone knows
而且大家都知道
The mobile phones you are using now
各位現在用的手機
In fact, when you pick up your mobile phone, it is transmitted to the base station.
其實你手機拿起來是傳到基地台
The base station is directly connected to the aperture of the sewer
基地台就直接到下水道的光圈
Then the aperture helps you run the longest distance
然後光圈幫你跑最長遠的路
Then the shortest way is actually to the base station
然後短的路其實都是到基地台
So this communication of light
所以這個光的通訊
In fact, it is to allow human civilization to have the so-called private message phone
事實上是讓人類文明能夠有所謂的私訊電話
The only way to have so-called various means of communication
有所謂的各式各樣的通訊的方式的唯一的方法
In addition, many optical instruments and cosmic hot cables
另外很多光學的儀器還有宇宙的燙索
Launch many artificial satellites from now on
從現在發射很多人造衛星
Many devices to explore the universe
很多探究宇宙的一些裝置
are actually optical devices
事實上都是一些光學裝置
So optical activities are actually very important in science
所以光學的活動事實上在科學上面是非常重要的
on culture
在文化上面
also in education
還有在教育上面
still in nature
還有在自然
and art
還有藝術上面
It's actually quite important
事實上也都相當重要
I won't go back one by one
我就不一一追溯
because time is limited
因為時間有限
In the last slide, this part is about the design of light and shadow in general
最後一張投影片講到這部分就是像一般來講的光影的設計
And the lighting in your home
還有就是各位在家裡面的照明
And the way these lights of the road project
還有道路的這些光的投射的方式
Course Study Astronomy Universe
當然研究天文宇宙
beautiful starry sky
美好的星空
I haven't seen the real Xinxin for a long time
很久很久沒有看到真正的心心
Because there is a lot of light pollution in the city
因為在城市裡面有很多的光害
Actually light is a very, very important thing
事實上光是非常非常重要的一件事情
For the environment
對環境來講
I'll explain more later
我等一下會更進一步說明
The bottom two are archaeological
底下這兩張是考古
this is in mexico with leda
這是在墨西哥用萊達
It's a radar made of lasers
就是雷射做的這樣子的雷達
Do some scans of some old ruins
對一些舊的遺址做一些掃描
After scanning, there are some remains of pyramids
掃描之後發現有一些金字塔的遺跡
Actually it's not very significant now
其實現在不是非常顯著
because after a long time
因為時間久了之後
It's all covered with dust
上面都被塵土淹蓋住了
But if you detect it optically
但是你如果用光學的方式去偵測的話
you can actually find
你事實上可以找到
Some are already weathered
有一些已經都就是經過風化
or thousands of years later
或者是幾千年之後
have turned into ruins like mud
都已經變成像泥土一樣的一些遺址
So in fact optical technology
所以事實上光學技術
It is very, very important to the development of human civilization
對人類文明的發展是非常非常重要的
OK, so this one was in 2015
好,那這個是在2015年
Covers of various magazines and periodicals
各式不同的一些雜誌期刊的封面
It's all about light
都是跟光有關係
In the end, some people even used optical communication
最後甚至於有人用光通訊的方式
Look at Europe is 27.8TB per second
看歐洲是27.8TB per second
That is, 27.8 TB of bits are transferred in one second
就是一秒鐘有27.8個TB的位元的傳輸
But in Africa it's actually only 397Gb
可是在非洲事實上只有397Gb
If this difference is made, the transmission speed will be nearly five or six hundred times worse.
那這一差的話就差了將近五六百倍的傳輸的速度
So it can be seen that the civilizations of various regions
所以可以看得出來各個地區的文明
In fact, it is closely related to optical communication or optical development.
事實上是跟光通訊或說光學發展是息息相關的
So if we define the development of civilization on this earth by this
所以如果由這個來界定這個地球的文明發展的話
in fact a way
事實上是一種方式
then say otherwise
那另外就說
Because the optical industry is called Fotonics Industry
因為光學的產業叫做Fotonics Industry
Fotonics are photons
Fotonics就是光子
Fotonics is the research knowledge of photons
Fotonics就是光子的研究學問
This field includes LED lighting
這個領域裡面包括LED 照明
Including image sensing
包括影像的感應
Communications including fiber optics
包括光纖的通訊
including precision optics
包括精密光學
Light sources including lasers
包括雷射的光源
including optical storage
包括光學的存儲
Includes flat display
包括平面的顯示
There is also an optical assist device
還有光輔打的裝置
What is an optical auxiliary device
什麼叫光輔打裝置
Optical auxiliary device is to convert photons into electrons
光輔打裝置就是把光子轉換成電子
Then it becomes energy that can be used by human beings
然後變成是人類可以使用的能源
Devices like solar cells
像太陽能電池之類的裝置
good
好
These areas have undergone major developments in human civilization
這些領域在人類文明裡面有重大的發展
There are also very significant developments in Taiwan
在台灣也是有非常重大的發展
Taiwan since 1996
台灣從1996年開始
industries with such optics
有這種光學的產業
the optical industry
這種光學產業
Improve every year
逐年都有提升
then you will ask me
那你會問我說
What is the approximate amount of this industry?
這個產業大概是有多少的金額
You can take a look
各位可以看一下
It is in the field of the nine items just now
就是剛剛這九項的領域裡面的
How many products we sell each year
每一年我們賣出去的產品有多少
It can be seen here
這邊可以看得出來
billions of billions each
各千百萬十億
$80 billion
800億美金
That's 80 billion US dollars
就是800億美金
We sell in Taiwan
我們台灣賣出去的
These optoelectronic related industries
這些光電相關的產業
$80 billion
800億美金
What is the largest of the 80 billion US dollars?
那800億美金裡面最大中的是什麼呢
it is this
是這個
This is the Fed Panel Display
這個是Fed Panel Display
flat panel display
就是平面顯示器
So this flat-panel display probably grew more than half of its output value
所以這個平面顯示器大概長了超過一半以上的產值
so in fact
所以事實上
Taiwan is actually in the world
台灣事實上在全世界
Play an important role
扮演重要的角色
Because the global market is
因為全球的市場是多少
Write 80 billion here
這邊寫800億
The global market is about 20 times bigger than ours
全球的市場大概比我們要大20倍
so we take 5 percent
所以我們占百分之5
we account for 5 percent
我們占百分之5
So the entire key market
所以整個關鍵市場
It is very important to Taiwan's people's livelihood technology
對台灣的民生科技是很重要的
employment, industrial development, scientific development of the country
就業、工業發展、國家的科學發展
is very important
是非常重要
So the Key Society of the Republic of China
所以中華民國關鍵學會
United Nations Cultural Organization
就跟聯合國家各文組織
There is also the cooperation of the International Wannian Engineering Society
還有國際萬年工程學會合作
promote this event
就推動這個活動
Activities in Taiwan
在台灣各項的活動
Specially invited other relevant
也特別邀請了其他相關的
像TISA、TVA、TVS、TOSA
像TISA、TVA、TVS、TOSA
and the Physical Society of the Republic of China
還有中華民國物理學會
Optoelectronic Society of the Republic of China
中華民國光電學會
These participate in an event like this
這些一起參加這樣子的一個活動
This activity is actually
這個活動事實上
In August 2014 we
我們在2014年8月就
Special invitation to Vice Chairman Sun Qingcheng
特別請副理事長孫慶成
Director of the Institute of Optoelectronics, Chuo University
中央大學光電所的所長
to represent us
去代表我們去參加
Then in this December of 2014
然後在這個2014年的12月
we have a very important
我們就有一個非常重要的
an opening ceremony
一個opening ceremony
Also invited this Mr. Zhang Zhou
也邀請了這個張周某先生
and the International Society for Optoelectronic Engineering in the United States
還有美國的國際光電工程學會的
CEO and Swedish
執行長還有瑞典的
Head of the Royal Academy Physics Group
皇家科學院物理小組的負責人
And there is our Academician Reid Cai
還有就是我們的里德財院士
participated in such an event together
一起參加了這樣一個活動
This is Academician Reid
這個是里德財院士
This is Zhang Zhou
這是張周某
This is the CEO of SPIE
這是SPIE的執行長
This is the chairman of Taiwan Optical Industry Federation
這個是台灣光學工業總會的理事長
We also have a lot of activities
我們也有一些很多的活動
I should not meet
我就不宜遇到
The first prize is to show you these activities
第一的獎就是秀給各位看這些活動
In various universities, various events to vent the beauty of light have also been held.
在各個大學也舉辦了各種發洩光之美
Or the official program is at the Institute of Optoelectronics, National Taiwan University
或者是正式的節目是在台灣大學光電所
Hosted by Principal Yang
由楊校長特別主持
We also invited Dr. Shi Dacheng, chairman of the Optoelectronics Technology Industry Association, to give a speech
我們也邀請了光電科技工業協經會的董事長石大成博士演講
Then, Professor Sun Qingheng was also sent to participate in the important activities of global RIL in Paris, France
然後也派了孫慶恆教授代表參加法國巴黎的全球的RIL的重要活動
It's the United Nations Organization for Science and Technology to participate in this conference
是聯合國家科人組織去參加這個大會
National Synchronization Assistance Center in this childhood Hsinchu, Taiwan
在台灣這個童年新竹的國家同步輔助中心
Director Guoshang also specially held the inauguration ceremony of Taiwan Photon Park
國上自主任也特別辦了台灣光子園的落成典禮
It has become a very important event for Taiwan in the international arena
變成台灣在國際上非常重要的一個活動
very big highlight
非常重大的亮點
Of course, there are various activities in this planetarium.
當然這個天文館還有各個活動
Including the lamp there will be an exhibition of Einstein's main lamp
包括燈會有一個安因斯坦的主燈展覽
Chairman of the Japanese Society of Government Studies of OSJ in Japan
日本的OSJ的日本官學學會的理事長
President of SPIE's International Conceptual Engineering Society
SPIE的國際觀念工程學會理事長
The chairman of the Taiwan Government-Academia Trade Union was also present.
還有台灣官學同業工會的理事長都出席了
Our event is in fact an international event
我們的活動事實上是一個國際性的活動
Invited Nam Kwong laser inventor Zhong Chunxiuer to give a speech in Taiwan
邀請了南光雷射的發明人中春修爾來台灣演講
We also organize activities for the International Year of Wisdom in various universities
也在各個大學辦理國際觀知年的活動
Also includes photoelectric week at Nangang International Exhibition Center
也包括在南港國際展覽中心辦光電週
There were about 50,000 to 60,000 people present
到場大概有五六萬人
So this event is actually a big event
所以這次的活動事實上是一個很大的活動
In fact, this activity is very
這個活動事實上非常多
It also includes organizing some activities in middle schools and high schools
也包括在國中跟高中辦一些
this briefing and some presentations
這個說明會和一些演講
There are also workshops with popular science lectures
也有科普講座的工作坊
from january to december
從1月一直到12月
There are various activities every month
每一個月都有各式各樣的活動
A total of more than 50 presentations
總共有超過50場的演講
In North, Central, South, and East
在北、中、南、還有東部都有辦理
For details, if you are interested, you can see
細節如果各位有興趣可以看
The RYL2015 International Year of Light Part Review
這個RYL2015國際光之年部分回顧
This page is actually
這個網頁事實上
at the United Nations
在聯合國家客文組織
Follow the website in Taiwan
跟在台灣的網頁上面
can see the link
都可以看到連結
There are movies and photos
裡面有電影、有照片
I won't go into details
我就不細講了
this is his link
這是他的連結
It is our Taiwan International Year of Light
就是我們台灣國際光之年的
Website, Lantern Festival website
網站、燈會的網站
There is also a link and address of the review video
還有回顧影片的連結跟地址
Designed by Sun Qingcheng and the director of the Key Institute of Sun Central University
孫慶成、孫中央大學關鍵所所長他設計的
It is this LOGO plus in Taiwan
就是這個LOGO之外加上在台灣
This is a mountain with three veins
這是一山三脈
Well, that is to say, all the people in Taiwan who participated in this activity
好,就是說全台參與這個活動的人
There are probably more than two thousand people
將近有大概超過兩千人
2,000 person-times, because including production officers and trainees
兩千人次,因為包括產官學員都有
To sum it up, why do you want to do this?
總結一下就是說為什麼要去做這件事情
because we think light is actually very important
因為我們認為光事實上是非常重要
It will have a major impact on Taiwan's future culture and people's livelihood technology
對台灣未來的文化跟民生科技都會有重大的影響
Those of us who may have bought stocks know that
我們可能有買股票的人都知道
At present, Largan is still the stock king or the stock queen.
目前大立光還是股王或者是股後吧
That is to say, mobile phones around the world
也就是說全球的手機
this lens
這個鏡頭
That's only us in Taiwan
那也只有我們台灣
This compound lens can be done
可以做到這種複合鏡頭
the size of a grain of rice
像米粒那麼大的大小
confidential optics
機密光學
Then the lens module like this
然後這樣子的透鏡模組
Can be marketed all over the world
可以行銷到全世界
Then everyone depends on us
然後人家都靠我們的
This confidential optical lens
這樣子的機密光學的透鏡
do this
來做這個
camera lens
照相機的鏡頭
So this is a very important development
所以這個是一個非常重要的一個發展
In addition to that
另外就是說
the year of international
這個國際觀之年
It's actually a rare opportunity
事實上是很難得的一個機會
Put us Taiwan on top of the international
讓我們台灣在國際上面
there is one
有一個
a chance to show
表現的一個機會
A platform to communicate with everyone
跟大家一起交流的一個平台
so
所以
We will work very hard to do this
我們就很努力的去做這件事
Well, I spent about ten minutes telling this story.
好我大概用了十幾分鐘講這個故事
Then I will report to you next time.
那接下來要跟各位報告的
is the recent story of optics
就是光學最近的故事
What happened to optics recently?
那光學最近發生些什麼事情呢
I'll probably tell you guys first
我大概會跟各位先講一下
what is photonics
什麼是photonics
that photonics
那photonics
You can imagine lasers, like this laser pointer
各位可以想像到雷射,像這隻雷射筆
Then CCD KEMENR, CCD KEMENR won the Nobel Prize
然後CCD KEMENR,CCD KEMENR拿了諾貝爾獎
This Guangqian Gaokun also won the Nobel Prize for Guangqian Communication
這個光千高坤做光千通訊也拿到諾貝爾獎
Then the focusing of light, because of optical focusing, we have microscopes and astronomical telescopes for such things
然後光的聚焦,因為光學聚焦,這樣的事情我們才會有顯微鏡,才會有天文望遠鏡
Then, solar cells, our southern campus is at Shalun Farm, which will become a demonstration base for green energy photoelectricity in the future
然後呢,太陽能電池,我們現在南部院區在沙輪農場那邊,將來會變成是一個綠能光電的一個示範的基地
Then, there will be solar cells everywhere
那會,到處都會是太陽能的電池
As for BioSensor, BioSensor has gradually become more and more important in Taiwan, because I don’t have
那BioSensor,BioSensor目前在台灣已經逐步的重要,因為我沒有
Showed a lot of other market development information, currently Taiwan's optoelectronics industry
秀出來很多其他的一些市場發展的資料,目前大概台灣的光電產業
In the past two years, this Bio Photonics has accounted for 8%
最近這一兩年這個Bio Photonics已經占了8%
Is to grow gradually from scratch
就是逐漸成長從零開始
Slowly start growing over five years
在五年內慢慢開始成長
Many things are Bio Sensors
很多東西都是Bio Sensor
And there is Bio Image
還有就是Bio Image
Bio Image actually spoke at Norbert Herschel in 2014
Bio Image事實上在2014年的Norbert Herschel講
Just for Bio Image
就是給Bio Image
If I work on this aspect, I will try to find a way to report to you.
這方面的工作的話我會再想辦法跟各位報告
So my next story will be divided into three parts
所以我接下來的故事會分成三個部分
The first part is Green Life
第一個部分是Green Life
The second one is Bin Light
第二個是Bin Light
The third part is Future World
第三個部分是Future World
What is Green Light What is Bin Light What is Future World
什麼是Green Light 什麼是Bin Light 什麼是Future World
I will take three examples individually and report to you
我會在個別取三個範例跟各位報告
那 Photonics for Green World
那 Photonics for Green World
That is to say now everyone knows this
就是說現在大家都知道這個
Human civilization has developed to this day
人類文明發展到今天
What everyone wants is a very clean
大家希望的是一個非常乾淨
A very healthy and hygienic environment
非常健康、非常衛生的一個環境
A very beautiful future world
非常美好的一個未來的世界
So we all say that we hope that we can not consume
所以都講就是說希望能夠不消耗
No matter what is consumed, nothing is consumed
不管是消耗什麼東西都不消耗
no waste
不浪費
And keep it very simple, very clean
然後維持非常簡單、非常乾淨
need to be able to do this
要做到這一點
In fact science is a very important development
事實上科學是一個非常重要的發展
So how to do this
所以怎麼樣做到這一點呢
The first point is to say
第一點就是說
Many things in human civilization are being explored
人類文明裡面很多的事情大家在探索
That is to say we used to do
就是說我們以前做的
But can we do better now
但是我們現在可不可以做得更好
One of the most typical is this solar auxiliary device
其中一個最典型的就是這個太陽能輔達裝置
What is a tutoring device basically?
輔導裝置基本上是什麼呢
basically it says
基本上它就是說
The sun's light travels 8 minutes to the earth
太陽光走了8分鐘到地球
Then humans on the earth develop some devices
然後地球上面的人類發展一些裝置
These devices convert the energy of this light into electrons
這些裝置把這些光的能量轉換成電子
convert photons into electrons
把光子轉換成電子
This electron can then be used to light a light bulb
然後這個電子可以拿來去做點亮燈泡
or cooking
或者是煮菜
Or do other uses of electric vehicles
或者是做其他的用途電動車
Harrie Walter of Caltech
加州理工的Harrie Walter
One of the world's leading teams in their lab
他們實驗室世界上最領先的一個團隊
Caltech also has one of the world's leading green energy centers
加州理工也有一個世界上最領先的一個綠能中心
he is the director of the center
他是中心主任
He proposed that on the solar cell
他就提出說在太陽能電池上面
put these very tiny nanoparticles
放這些非常微小的奈米顆粒
These nanoparticles allow these light
這些奈米顆粒可以讓這些光
During this process
在這個過程中
Generate more electrons during the action
作用的過程中產生更多的電子
can be more efficient
效率可以更高
How to put these nanometer metal particles
怎麼樣放這些奈米的金屬顆粒呢
can be placed on the most surface
可以放在最表面
It can be placed at the interface of this semiconductor
可以放在這個半導體的界面的地方
That can also be placed behind this
那也可以放在這個背後
Do some unavoidable structure behind
背後做一些難免的結構
So they did a lot of experiments like this
所以他們做了很多這樣子的實驗
to study
去研究
It was found that the efficiency can be improved
那發現效率可以提升
Then how much would you say the efficiency has improved?
那你會說效率到底提升多少
The highest and ultimate efficiency of human civilization
那人類文明目前最高的極致的效率
That is, 100 photons
就是說100個光子
How many can be converted into electrons
有多少個可以轉換成電子
about 20 or so
大概20幾個
What about the 20?
那20幾個裡面呢
if it can improve
如果它可以提升
Assume 10%
假設10%
That means
那就是說
That's 20, that's two more
就是20個就是多兩個
You may not mind
那各位可能不以為意
But what?
可是呢
The photon is actually very, very large
這個光子事實上是非常非常大的
energy from the sun to the earth
太陽給予地球的能量
It's actually very, very strong
事實上是非常非常強的
very rich
非常豐富的
a lot of
非常多的
So a very small increase in efficiency
因此非常小的一個效率的提升
In fact, it is a very big step in human civilization.
事實上在人類文明是一個非常重大的一大步
so this is a very important thing
所以這是非常重要的一件事情
Therefore, all countries in the world, especially advanced countries, attach great importance to this point.
所以世界各國都尤其是先進國家都非常重視這一點
We are short of a round of professors at Tsinghua University in Taiwan
我們台灣清華大學缺一輪教授
His Tianan battery like this in CIGS
他在CIGS的這樣子的Tianan電池
There are many kinds of Tianan batteries
就是其中Tianan電池有很多種
Some are using Silicon with fine
有些是用Silicon 用細
Some are made of diversified metals
有些是用多元化的金屬
Tianan battery made of multiple compound semiconductor materials
有多元的複合的半導體材料來做出來的Tianan電池
it incorporates particles of gold
它參入了金的顆粒
There is also an east-west interlayer of the fluidized compartment.
還有流化隔的一層東西夾層在這裡面
He found that he could actually improve this efficiency
他發現他事實上這個效率可以提升
Can be increased from 8.3% to 10.3%
可以提升從8.3%到10.3%
increased by 2%
就提升了2%
You'd say 2% is no big deal
你會說2%沒有什麼了不起
Actually 2% is pretty big
其實2%非常了不起
Because 0.5% is a big deal
因為0.5%就很了不起了
Don't talk about 2%
不要講2%
So his job is a very important job
所以他的工作是非常重要的一個工作
And he illuminates from different angles
而且他不同的角度去照射
no mezzanine like this
沒有這樣子的一個夾層
with such a mezzanine
跟有這樣一個夾層
His performance can be from 350 nm wavelength to
他的表現可以從350奈米的波長到
This wavelength of nearly 1000 nanometers
這個將近1000奈米的波長
have a very good performance
都有非常好的一個表現
very balanced performance
非常均衡的表現
for different angles of incidence
對不同的入射的角度
He can have a very high absorption
他都可以有非常高的吸收
it's not easy
這是很不容易的一件事情
What about Professor Chen Wenwen from National Taiwan University?
這個台大的陳文章教授呢
he is also very clever
他呢也非常巧妙
He made one like this
他把這樣子的一個
This is a PVP plain glue
這是一種PVP的素膠
then snag
然後抽絲
in the process of spinning
抽絲的過程中
It puts silver grains inside this easy
它把銀的顆粒放在這個容易裡面
then snag
然後抽絲
Then when spinning
然後抽絲的時候
It first puts a small metal carrier
它先放一個金屬的一個小的一個承載物
and turn like this
然後就這樣轉
like faux sand
就像仿沙一樣
when it was like sand
那仿沙的時候
you will find
你會發現到
It can imitate sand like this first
它可以先這樣子仿沙
Then it can turn the artificial sand 90 degrees again
然後它可以再把仿沙轉90度
Then imitate sand like this
然後再這樣仿沙
After imitation sand
仿沙之後
Inside the plastic PVP inside
這裡面的塑膠的PVP裡面
Contains some gold particles
就含了一些金顆粒
Containing percentages from 1.39 to 0.36 to 0.07
含的百分比從1.39到0.36到0.07
The less it contains, of course the finer the silk can be drawn
含的越少當然就可以拉得絲越細
kinda like silk
有點像蠶絲一樣
Then it does this thing
然後它做了這個事情
It then puts this thing inside the solar cell
它再把這個東西擺在這個太陽能電池裡面
This organic semiconductor solar cell
這種有機半導體的太陽能電池
at this
在這個
top of electrode
電極的上面
then he found
然後他發現
It's in the spectrum of visible light
他的這個在可見光的光譜裡面
his external quantum efficiency
他的這個外部量子效率
Can be increased from 40% 50% to 60%
可以從40% 50%提升到60%
So this is also a very important development.
所以這個是也是一個非常重大的一個發展
So our scientist in Taiwan
所以我們台灣的這個科學家
Work very hard to do these state-of-the-art work
非常努力的去做這些最先進的工作
Also at the same time in this
另外同時在這個
Rice University
Rice University
Rice University in America
美國的稻米大學
they have a very amazing one
他們有一位非常了不起的一位
American Academy of Sciences
美國的三院院士
He heard that he is now an academician of four academies
他聽說現在已經是四個院的院士
called Niamihara's
叫做Niamihara's
He was the first in the world to propose
他是世界上第一個提出就是
Put this Daimi's metal pellets
把這個代米的金屬顆粒
This kind of photothermal therapy for cancer
拿來做癌症的這種光熱治療
Just let the metal particles like this absorb
就是讓這樣子的金屬顆粒去吸收
Then heat the cancer cells to death
然後把癌細胞給熱死
This is their animal experiment
這是他們的動物實驗
And they've been approved by the FDA
而且他們已經獲得FDA的核准
to do some human experiments
去做一些人體的實驗
12 days after the tumor
這個腫瘤經過12天之後
just end up scum
就結尬渣
becomes very very small
就變成非常非常小
That is to say, it is very effective to do such a thing
那就是說很有效的去做這樣的事情
Those are the things that make human life
那這些都是讓人類的生活
some things that could be better
可以更美好的一些事情
Professor Huang Guozhu at Tsinghua University in Taiwan
那在台灣清華大學的黃國柱教授
too done such a thing
太做了這樣的事情
but he is smarter
但是他更聰明
He took the nanoparticle
他把那個奈米顆粒
made like a sea urchin
做成像海膽一樣
one by one thorn
一顆一顆刺
then you can see this sea urchin
那你可以看到這顆海膽
This is the magnetic marker at 100 nanometers
這是100奈米的這個磁標
Then this is about a few hundred nanometers
那這個的話大概就是幾百個奈米
Five or six hundred nanometers
五六百個奈米
such sea urchin
這樣海膽
then a lot of thorny words
然後很多刺的話
he made the mouse
他讓這個老鼠
to deduce
去演繹
After having an Essie bag culture
有埃西包培養之後
Let particles like this adsorb on the Essie bag
讓這樣子的顆粒去吸附在埃西包上面
Then it shines infrared light in
然後它照紅外線的光進來之後
It can generate more of these free machines
它可以產生更多的這些自由機
Then heat the root and kill the Essie bag
然後把根熱 然後把埃西包殺死
Then the Essie bag will shrink
然後埃西包就會萎縮
this was very very successful
這個非常非常成功
You may ask, what is the relationship between the thorn and the particle?
你會問說這個刺跟顆粒有什麼關係呢?
Because they make glutinous rice balls, why do you make sea urchins?
因為人家做湯圓 為什麼你要做海膽?
It's simple, stab a lot of words
很簡單 刺很多的話
It is easier to receive these light and generate heat
它比較容易接收這些光產生熱
So this is easy to do
所以這個就很容易做到
Ms. Liu Ruxi from the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University
台大化學系的劉如希老師
he is better
他更厲害
He should do the thorn, it's not easy to do it small
他應該要做那個刺 要做的小 很不容易
so he made it small
所以他就做得很小
You see this is a 20 nanometer scale
你看這是20奈米的尺標
The one just now was a 100-nanometer scale
剛剛那個是100奈米的尺標
5. As big as 600 nanometers
5、600奈米那麼大
There is a limit to how many pills you can swallow
你能夠吞幾顆是有限的
If it is very small, it can swallow a lot
很小很小的話就可以吞很多
swallow a lot of words
吞很多的話
Ant Xiong Bin
螞蟻熊斌
it's powerful
它的力量就很大
so you can
所以就可以
It is easy to enter directly from the cell membrane
很容易就直接從細胞膜就進來了
because it's too small
因為它太小
After cell membrane invasion
細胞膜入侵之後
Demonstrate like this
像這個就示範出來說
You cover this one up
你光一罩罩這一塊
that cancer cell died
那個癌細胞死掉
these are cancer cells
這些都是癌細胞
are cancer cells
都是癌細胞
Cancer cells cultured on glass
培養在玻璃上的癌細胞
Then you light mask
那你這個光一罩
because these cancer cells
因為這些癌細胞
After swallowing such small particles
都吞了那麼小的顆粒之後
easy to kill
很容易就被殺死掉
So this is a very interesting development
所以這個是非常有趣的發展
Then Li Xianming from the Institute of Chemistry, Academia Sinica
那我們中研院化學所的李賢明
researcher
研究員
he is better
他更厲害
Because just after the light went down
因為剛剛這個光照下去之後
Your skin and flesh will block some of the light
你的皮膚跟肉會擋住一些光
Can't get in
打不進去
So he wanted a hood
所以他就想要一罩
He said he could get in
他說能夠打進去的
It must be infrared light with a relatively long wavelength
一定是要波長比較長的紅外線的光
So he put these things just now
所以他把剛剛這些東西
put on a so-called up-conversion material
放上一個所謂的上轉換的材料
Up-conversion means that I use a long wavelength to enter
上轉換就是說我打一個長的波長進去
it converts it to a shorter wavelength
它會把它轉換成短的波長
But you clean the skin and these tissues of these animals
但是你清過皮膚跟這些動物的這些組織
When hitting these refugee particles that can kill cancer cells
打到這些可以去殺死癌細胞的難民顆粒上面的時候
it converts
它才轉換
so it doesn't waste the light
所以它不會把這些光給浪費掉
and it can go deep into the organization
而且它可以深入到組織裡面
Therefore, Professor Li Xianming and Researcher Li Xianming's
所以李賢明教授李賢明研究員的
This so-called up-conversion
這樣子所謂的上轉換的
It's easy for you to see
就是很容易各位可以看得到
it uses something like this upconversion
它用這種上轉換的東西
allows you to see these cells very clearly
就可以讓你看到這些細胞非常清楚
this is a very important development
這個是非常重要的發展
just talked about green
剛剛講到綠色
Green must be related to the environment
綠色一定是跟環境有關係
So this is British
所以這個是英國的
Professor Durant of Inpirit College
Inpirit College的Durant教授
He has one idea
他就有一個發想一個
a future environment
未來的一個環境
Future environment sun shines down
未來環境太陽光照下來
and then in this various ways
然後這種各式各樣的方式
convert sunlight energy into chemical energy
把太陽光的光能轉換成化學能
or converted into this mechanical energy
或者是轉換成這種機械能
or converted into electrical energy
或者是轉換成電能
Then store energy in this way
那用這種方式把能量儲存起來
use as a human
作為人類的使用
Then don't develop something like nuclear energy, which is very dangerous
然後不去發展像危險性很高的核能
Or not to develop the highly dangerous thermal power generation
或者是不去發展危險性很高的火力發電
things like burning coal
燒煤這樣子的事情
Because in fact, the PN2.5 produced by burning coal
因為其實燒煤產生的PN2.5
Worse than a nuclear power plant
比核能電廠還可怕
So here are some of his wonderful thoughts
所以這是他的美好的一些想法
but all these beautiful thoughts
但是這所有美好的想法
It involves the efficiency of converting photons into electrons
裡面牽扯到就是光子轉換成電子的效率的問題
The problem of the efficiency of converting photons into electrons
那光子轉換成電子的效率的問題
In 1972, the Japanese discovered a very important thing, which is the effect of beauty in light.
日本人在1972年的時候就特別發現到一個非常重要的就是一種光處美的效應
There is a semiconductor carbon dioxide, which can effectively convert photons into electrons
有一種半導體二氧化碳,它可以有效的去讓光子轉換成電子這件事情
Happens when it's unlikely, becomes a lot when it's rare
在不可能發生的時候發生,在發生很少的狀況下變成發生很多
So a very important milestone is the hydrolysis experiment called Guangximei
所以很重要的一個里程碑就是叫做光處美的水解實驗
Such a substance of carbon dioxide is called Guangchumei substance
這樣子的一個二氧化碳的物質叫做光處美的物質
You may have seen that there are many toilets in Taiwan that are written by Guang Chumei.
各位可能已經看到台灣有很多馬桶是寫光處美馬桶
Then many supplies write about what are the cosmetic products used for light treatment? They are used for antibacterial
然後很多用品寫光處美用品拿來什麼?拿來做抗菌
Deodorizing and antibacterial, because it will produce some
除臭抗菌,因為光一照了之後它就會產生一些
These electrons make bacteria uncomfortable
這些電子就會讓細菌不舒服
prevent bacteria from growing
讓細菌就不會生長
It can also be used for water treatment
也可以來做水的處理
And do water decomposition
還有做水的分解
There are many other good uses
還有很多種很好的一些用途
That Century Han did the best
那世紀漢做的最好的
Professor Yang Peidong from Berkeley
是博克萊的楊培東教授
He developed something like this
他發展了這樣子的一些
Some very special electrodes for hydrolysis
很特殊的一些水解用的電極
This electrode has these photocatalyst nanoparticles
這個電極上面放著這些光觸媒的奈米顆粒
Then he can effectively
然後呢他可以有效的
Speed ​​up the hydrolysis rate of such a
把這樣子的一個水解的速率加快
efficiency improvement
效率提升
Professor Liu Ruxi, Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University
台灣的台大化學系劉儒熙教授
He is also working very hard on this aspect.
他呢也很努力的在做這一方面
That is not lost to Professor Yang Peidong of Berkeley University
那也不輸給博克萊大學的楊培東教授
They use this special effect of surface electric resonance
他們用這個表面電章共振的這個特特別的一個效果
On such a photocatalyst, some small nanoparticles are adsorbed
在這樣子的一個光觸媒上面又在吸附了一些很小的奈米顆粒
These are tiny nanoparticles that allow incoming light to generate photoelectrons
這些很小的奈米顆粒它會讓進來的光產生光電子
Then let these photoelectrons oscillate inside
然後又會讓這些光電子在裡面震盪
It's just the cloud wrapping around and never going away
就是雲回繞一直不走
It's not like you come in and have a talk and then leave to play a safe ball.
不是說進來談一下就走打平安球這樣
it doesn't come in, it stays in
它不是進來就一直在裡面
So it can effectively localize photons in a small range
所以它可以有效的把光子局域在很小的範圍內
and then to produce a strong effect
然後去產生很強的一個作用
This effect allows the photochemical reaction to produce hydrolysis
這個作用可以讓光化學反應產生做水解
So some experiments like this are conducted by Chen Yulin, Department of Physics, National Taiwan University.
所以這樣子的一些實驗在台大物理系陳玉琳
This Mr. Chen is doing some interesting things in my laboratory
這個陳老師他就在我的實驗室就做一些很有趣的事情
He just took the discarded CD and took it
他就把廢棄用的光碟片然後拿去
do an interesting experiment
做一個很有趣的實驗
That is to say, on the CD for flight
就是說,飛行用的光碟片上面
It is very simple to let it grow some small light and beautiful materials
很簡單的讓它長一些很小的光處美的材料
Then put this flying CD drive
然後把這個飛行用的光碟機
just hug me
就是直接抱過來
and put it in here
然後放在這裡面
Then it can put this dye
然後它就可以把這個染料
some dyes just do the processing
一些染料就是做處理
After processing these chemical dyes
處理之後這些化學的染料
will become
就會變成
At first a colored false base
起先是有顏色的假基層
it is a standard dye
它是一個標準的染料
Then do it and suck it up from above
然後來做從上面吸上去
dripping down on this flying disc
滴下來滴在這個飛行用的光碟片上
The chicken soup underneath will turn into clear water
底下這個雞湯就變清水
Just ask me where those dye molecules go
你就問我說那些染料分子跑到哪裡去
Then CO2 turns into H2O and runs away
然後再CO2變成H2O就跑掉了
Just dispersed in the air and went away
就異散在空氣之中就走掉了
so what can he do with it
所以他可以拿來做什麼事
It can be used for waste water treatment
他可以拿來做廢水處理
Wastewater Treatment Jobs
廢水處理的工作
because he can decompose some
因為他可以分解一些
decompose
decompose
It is to give some harmful chemical substances to
就是把一些有害的化學的物質給
spies interrupted
間諜給打斷掉
Then what
然後呢
what about this matter
那這件事情呢
It's actually just a small project
其實只是一個很小的project
Projects taught to students
教學生做的project
AAS
結果後來被美國官學學會
Also by BBC News in London, UK
還有被英國的倫敦的BBC News
evening News
晚間新聞
just say you know
就說你知道嗎
The Taiwanese took the CD for the plane
台灣人拿那個飛機用的光碟片
to treat sewer water
去處理下水道的水
that water is still drinkable
那個水還可以喝
You know when word gets around
你就知道這個話傳來傳去之後
global report
全球就報導
And then we got close to this one or two hundred letters
然後我們收到將近這個一兩百封信
asked us to give them that movie
要求我們把那個電影給他們
they are going to do
他們要去做
Then there are many high school students in the United States
然後還有美國很多高中生
Said they were going to bake
說他們要做烘烤可
do this
要做這件事
good
好
Then our hard science center
那我們硬科中心
He's in the researcher, he's actually just been in water treatment
他在研究員,他事實上剛剛那是水處理
In fact, he told me that a while ago, everyone was very careful with food
事實上他對前一陣子,大家對食物都很小心
Especially pesticides, and some toxic chemicals
尤其是農藥,還有一些有毒的化學物質
Affects food, he does one thing in particular
影響到食物,他特別做一件事情
He asked if there was any way to quickly test the residual pesticides
他就說有沒有什麼方法可以快速的檢驗殘餘的農藥
So he just made normal slides like this
所以他就做普通的這種投影片
It's an A4-sized slide, and he used it to make some Naimi structures on it
就是A4大小的投影片,他拿去做一些耐米的結構在上面
Then, in these Nami structures, he can build them piece by piece
然後這些耐米結構裡面,他就可以一塊一塊的
He can lower the things you want to test on top
他就可以把你要檢驗的東西低在上面
For example, tearing down the leaves and smashing them into pieces, lowering them to the top
例如說拆葉子把它打爛,低在上面
Then you can see the real-time test from the above performance
然後從上面的表現就可以看得到即時的檢驗
This one doesn't seem to work
這個是好像不會工作
Let me tell you that this is its Akuan No. 1
我跟各位報告這是它的阿寬1號
This is a plastic sheet in A4 size
這是A4大小的一個塑膠紙
it just has a thing
它就是有一個東西
just put it in
就擺進去
Stamped stamped stamped
蓋章蓋章蓋章
covered many, many nanostructures
就蓋了很多很多的奈米結構
These nanostructures are stamped one by one like this
這些奈米結構就是像這樣一個一個印章
These seals are sensors
這些印章都是一些感應器
This sensor sees with the naked eye
這個感應器用肉眼看
very clever
就非常靈靈
Its sensitivity is a world record
它的sensitivity是破世界紀錄
broken world record
破世界紀錄
very high sensitivity
非常高的靈敏度
You can see the color directly with the naked eye
可以直接用肉眼看顏色就可以看到
So it recently did an interesting technology transfer
所以它最近再做一個有趣的技術移轉
Just put your phone directly on its sensor
就是把手機直接來照它的sensor
You can see it just inside this
就可以看得到它剛剛這個裡面
The concentration of that glory is from the right
那個榮耀的濃度從右邊是
glory few to left glory many
榮耀很少到左邊榮耀很多
You can see how much glory you have when you drop it
你滴上去一看就知道你的榮耀多少
You can know in which grid
在第幾格就可以知道
So the phone can take a picture
所以手機就可以照下來
After taking a picture with the phone
手機照下來之後
The mobile phone has an APP
手機有一個APP
I can tell you
就可以告訴你說
You are now honored, what is the glory in Zen language?
你現在榮耀 禪語榮耀是多少
he told me yesterday
他昨天跟我講說
Now the most commonly tested is edamide
現在平常測的最多是易達安
The limit of Yidaan residue is 0.5ppm
易達安殘留的限量是0.5ppm
to 3 ppm
到3個ppm
Usually more than 3 ppm
通常就是超過了3個ppm
The limit of how deep they can be measured is 0.01
他們可以深測的極限值是0.01
That is to say, they have high seniority
就是說他們年領度很高
This is what they actually measured
這是他們實際上測出來的結果
They will cooperate with Glory
他們跟榮耀會有合作
at the end of last year
去年年底的時候
This job also held a press conference
這個工作還開了一個記者會
It's the honor meeting they opened
是榮耀會他們開的
So some work on this
所以這方面的一些工作
In fact, Taiwan does not
事實上台灣也沒有
I have also done a lot, and it is very advanced
也做了非常多,而且非常先進
It's just that many people are very busy with certain things
只是很多的人都很忙於一些事情
don't know its development
並不知道它的發展
So today I hope to have the opportunity to report to you
所以今天才希望能夠有機會跟大家報告
The second part is about this
那第二部分就是在講這個
Part of BinLine
BinLine的部分
The part of the BinLine that says
BinLine的部分就是說
production of light, use of light
光的產生,光的使用
And what about these things?
還有這些東西要怎麼樣去
some of the latest developments
最新的一些發展
Professor Xiang Zhang at Berkeley University
在目前博克萊大學的張祥教授
He is also an academician of our Academia Sinica
也是我們中研院的院士
and Terry Olden from Northwestern
還有西北大學的Terry Olden
The two of them are in this
他們兩位分別是在這種
The smallest light source in the world
世界上最小的光源
well done lab
做的相當好的實驗室
One is nanorods with so-called fluidized spacers
一個是用所謂的流化隔的奈米棒棒
on a silver surface
放在銀的表面上面
Then the world's smallest
然後就產生了世界上最小的
Laser, then this is the spectrum of the light emitted by the laser
雷射,那這個是雷射發出來的光的光譜
Very uniform, very good
非常的這個均衣,非常的好
Then the other Terry Ogden they use a different fluid to flow through
那另外這個Terry Ogden他們用不同的這個液體流過
A metal particle like this will be found to say
這樣子的一個金屬的顆粒,然後呢會發現到說
They can produce different liquids when flowing through such particles
他們可以產生不同的液體流過這樣的顆粒的時候
If the refractive index is different, the wavelength of the laser light it produces is not the same
折射率不一樣的話,它產生出來的雷射光的波長是不一樣的
Then the two of them are currently known to be the best in the world.
那他們兩個是目前大家都知道世界上做的最好的
Then we in Taiwan might as well let Professor Guo Shangzhi of Tsinghua University
那我們台灣也不妨多讓清華大學國上志教授
After the two of them, he also published the so-called
他在他們兩位之後呢也發表了用所謂的這個
Nano Isshiki made of a column made of nitrided nano
氮化加的奈米的這樣子的一個柱子做的奈米的一色
The nano particles
那這個奈米的顆粒
What is the difference between Nanolaser and Nanolaser just now?
奈米雷射跟剛剛的奈米雷射有什麼差別
The nano-laser just now is not a semiconductor laser
剛剛的奈米雷射不是半導體雷射
That's a semiconductor laser
那這個是半導體雷射
And it is at long temperature
而且它是在長溫下
Yishi that can be produced at a long temperature
在長溫下就可以產生的一色
And its efficiency and the light produced by its power
而且它的效率跟它的功率產生的出來的光
are very very strong
都非常非常的強
And the quality of light is much better than before
而且光的品質也遠比先前
Much better quality published by any other lab
任何其他實驗室發表出來的品質好很多
So teacher Guo's nano laser
所以國老師的奈米雷射
In fact its directionality
事實上它的方向性
And its temperature control is very, very good
還有它的溫度的控制都非常非常好
I won't go into details
細節我就不多講了
In addition, Mr. Guo recently developed a variety of different wavelengths
另外最近國老師他也發展出來各種不同波長
that is, different colors
也就是各種不同顏色的
various nanolasers
各種各樣的奈米雷射
And they're doing really well
而且表現都非常好
This is the smallest semiconductor laser in the world
這個是以資世界上最小的半導體雷射
It's only 50 nanometers wide and 200 nanometers long
它的寬度只有50奈米,長度是200奈米
This record has not been broken so far
到目前為止這個紀錄沒有人破
So it is the light of our Taiwan
所以算是我們臺灣之光
Well, he's also the director of our Synchrotron Radiation Center.
那他同時也是我們同步輻射中心的主任
Professor of Department of Physics, Tsinghua University
清大物理系的教授
In addition, this Professor Zhang Xiangzhang
另外呢,這個張祥張教授
He also developed a type that is like a disc
他也發展出來一種就是像一個圓盤型的
But this disk is very small
但這個圓盤非常小
Everyone, take a look, this is 1micron
各位看一下這是1micron
If it is 1micron, everyone knows that your hair is about 500micron
1micron的話,各位知道你的頭髮大概是500micron
5 percent of your hair
就是你頭髮的5百分之一
so small a small ring
那麼小的一個小的環
plate, this plate will produce this circular circular resonant gun laser
盤子,這個盤子會產生這種圓形的這種圓形共振槍的雷射
His advantage is that he is very
他的好處是他非常
very very narrow wavelength
波長非常非常的狹窄
very very thin
非常非常的細
Such research is rare
這樣子的研究是很難得的
Professor No. 4 of the Department of Electrical Engineering, National Taiwan University
我們台灣台大電機系核四號教授
He also used similar techniques in two-dimensional materials
他也用類似的技術在二維的材料
Molidae
Molidae safi
It's on the sample of second fluidized wood
就是二流化木的樣品上面
found that if you put a sample like this
發現到說如果把這樣子的一個樣品
The resulting quantum efficiency
產生出來的量子效率
is the efficiency with which photons generate electrons
就是光子產生電子的效率
Can be improved from 0.9% to 99%
可以提升從0.9%變成99%
look this is very very bright
你看這個非常非常的亮
emit a lot of light
發很多的光出來
It's unfortunate that he was caught by this Arab
那很不幸的他被這個阿拉伯的
this
這個
Saudi Abo
Saudi Abo
dig this corner
這個挖角挖去
University Awareness in Saudi Abo
在Saudi Abo的大學認知
He is no longer in National Taiwan University
他現在已經不在台大了
he did very very well
他做得非常非常好
Of course, Professor Lu Luxi Liu of National Taiwan University
那當然台大的魯魯希劉教授
he in the past few years
他在過去這幾年
He also did a very, very good job
他也是做得非常非常傑出
I just mentioned that he made all kinds of
剛剛講到他做的各式各樣的
Materials for nano optoelectronics
奈米光電的材料
In fact his most famous
事實上他最有名的
All LED companies in Taiwan
就全台灣所有做LED的公司
hire him as a consultant
都請他當顧問
It's his fluorescent powder
就是他做的螢光粉
he put this
他把這種
Magnolite with four positive ions
帶四個正離子的猛
of this float
的這種浮化物
He tried to get him some grooming
他把他想辦法去做一些修飾
then produce fluorescence
然後產生螢光
Then the color temperature of the fluorescent light it produces
那他產生出來的螢光的色溫
very very very human
非常非常非常的適合人類
that is
就是說
The previous color temperature was too high
以前的色溫都太高
after too high
太高了之後
Your eyes get dizzy after looking at it for a long time
你的眼睛看久之後會暈眩
Then the color temperature it produces is very mild
那他產生的色溫是很溫和的
relatively low temperature
溫度比較低
that won't hurt you
那不會傷害到你的
It is a nerve, and it will not produce some sequelae such as white viscera
是神經,也不會產生白內臟之類的一些後遺症
Speaking of this, in fact there is a Chen Yuren in our center, Professor Chen
講到這個,事實上我們中心有一位陳裕仁,陳教授
He is very interested in this, he told me since I knew him
他對這個很有興趣,他從我認識他,他就告訴我說
He specializes in semiconductor optoelectronics, that is, someone who makes things like Guo Shangzhi and Guo Teacher
他是專門做半導體光電的,就是做像國上志、國老師這樣子的東西的人
He said that they found that they grow vegetables when they are very popular in Taiwan recently
他說他們發現,他們最近台灣很流行就去種菜
Use this semiconductor light source to grow vegetables
用這種半導體的光源去種菜
You say crazy, why don't you grow vegetables outside
你說神經病,為什麼不在外面種菜
Planting vegetables outside, there will be insects after the light is on, and there is no way to control the environment
在外面種菜,光照了之後也會有蟲,而且環境沒有辦法控制
Then when the typhoon comes, the vegetables will not grow
然後颱風天來的時候,菜就不長
So one dish costs hundreds of dollars, very expensive
所以菜一顆就好幾百塊,很貴
So they say I grow vegetables by hand
所以他們就說我用人工種菜
the idea is very nice
這個想法非常美好
Because our semiconductor industry in Taiwan is very good
因為我們台灣半導體的產業非常好
So LED made the world's number one
所以做LED做了全世界第一名
Use LED as light source to grow vegetables
用LED來做光源來種菜
sell it to those deserts
把它賣給那些沙漠
Or sell to those Arab countries
或者是賣給那些阿拉伯國家
it or those with bad environment
它或者是環境不好的那些
Very harsh places like the North Pole and the South Pole
很惡劣的地方像北極南極
The kind of area where it is dark for half a year
半年都是天黑的那種地區
isn't it good
不是很好嗎
but he said he told me
可是他說他告訴我
This vegetable has just been planted with a lot of technology and new regulations to grow vegetables
這個菜剛剛去種很多科技新規去種菜
and after planting
然後種了之後
Wow, the vegetables are growing so fast, so beautiful, so happy
哇 菜長得好快好漂亮好高興
And it is a water root plant, absolutely no pesticides
而且是水根植物絕對沒有從沒有農藥
Take it up and eat it, it makes a crackling sound
拿起來又吃吃起來咔嚓嚓的響
But that dish is neither sweet nor fragrant nor tasty
可是那個菜不甜不香又不好吃
It is different from the natural vegetables outside
跟外面天然的菜就是不一樣
Then after many people give up
然後經過很多人就放棄
after that segregation testimony
那隔離證詞之後
Some people slowly get the hang of it, he said it's not right
有些人慢慢抓到訣竅,他說不對
He said what kind of light the vegetables should be exposed to when they were young
他說菜在小的時候應該要照什麼光
When will it grow and when will it shine?
長到什麼時候要照什麼時候光
When it grows up to this time, it needs to be illuminated by this light, and when it is grown up, it must be illuminated by that light
長到這個時候要照這個光,長到那個時候要照那個光
Then what kind of light should I shine on the next few days?
然後第幾天要照什麼樣的光
That vegetable tastes delicious, and it's even better than vegetables grown outside
那個菜吃起來才會好吃,而且比外面種的菜還好吃
That becomes a very ceremonial thing
那就變成是非常學儀的一件事情
And what's even more strange is that he said that the light is terrible
然後更奇怪的是他說這個光很可怕的
That is to say, after the people who make LEDs use a lot of light
就是說他們做LED的人大量的使用了光之後
Discover the light that your human eyes see
發現你這個人的眼睛看到的光
Thought it was all the same, it's not
以為它都是一樣,其實不是
It's not just you that affects your sleep
它不只是你會影響到你的睡眠
and with your nervous system
而且跟你的神經系統
and your behavior
還有跟你的這種行為的舉止
and your mood
還有你的心情
And you are sports
還有你這個就是運動的
and your ability, and your memory
還有你的能力,還有你的記憶力
Also, your hormones
還有就是說你的荷爾蒙
and yours
還有你的這個
This cycle of physiological cellular responses
生理的細胞的反應的這個周期
It also has something to do with your biological clock.
還有你的這個生理時鐘都有關係
So it's the same with people
所以對人也是這樣子
The same goes for dishes
對菜也是一樣
that dish at different times
那菜在不同的時期
In fact, the light he wants to be thin is different.
事實上他想要瘦的光是不一樣的
so this is amazing
所以這個是很神奇的
So they started playing with the light
所以他們就開始在玩弄這個光
Especially playing around with this different wavelength
尤其是玩弄這個不同波長
light sources of different colors
不同顏色的光源
Then find a dense like this
然後找到這樣子的一個密集
recipe to do what they want to do
recipe來做完成他們想要做的事情
Then this involves some photochemical reactions
那這個就牽涉到一些光化學反應
I won't go into details about that
那細節我就不多講了
Well, this Chenye man, Professor Chen, is very powerful
好,這個陳業人陳教授他就很厲害
So this design varies
所以這個設計各式各樣不同的
Refugee structure produces light of different wavelengths
難民的結構產生不同的波長的光
some like this, some with their heads off
有些是這樣子的,有些是頭斷掉的
Some are pointy, some have broken heads
有些是尖尖的,有些是頭斷掉的
This kind of rice pillar
這種耐米的柱子
then it produces different light
然後它就會產生不同的光
Here you can see different colors of light
這邊各位可以看到不同顏色的光
Red Dust Yellow Green Blue Electronics
紅塵黃綠藍電子
Wavelength and its distribution
波長還有它的分布
all knowledge
都是一些學問
these things are fun
這些東西很好玩
Another thing is
另外有一個事情是
Our Researcher Li Chaohuang
我們李超皇研究員
He likes to observe some behaviors of cells
他很喜歡去觀察細胞的一些行為
he discovered that cells
他發現到說細胞
see a cell, it's a dwarf cell
看到一個細胞,這是一個矮細胞
Here is red light, the wavelength is 1064
這邊打紅色的光,波長是1064
Violet light here, the wavelength is 405
這邊打紫色的光,波長是405
As a result, the cell is very happy, and it continues to grow
結果細胞這邊很高興,它就繼續長大
It's not happy here, it wants to retract its feet
這邊它不高興,它要把腳收回來
After a period of time, the cells
經過一段時間之後,細胞
So it means that even a single cell has a good understanding of light.
所以代表說連單一個細胞它都對光是有喜悟
have likes and dislikes
有喜好跟不喜好
It comes from a study like this
它從這樣子一個研究裡面
You can see that this is a culture of cancer cells
各位可以看到這是一個癌細胞的培養的培養品
It hits a triangle with a light hitting this place
它打一個三角形的一個光打在這個地方
Let's hit a square light here
跟打一個正方形的光打在這邊
after a long time
久而久之之後
Where the light is lit, the cells are scattered
打光的地方這些細胞都散開來了
where it doesn't like to be in this 473 nanometer light
它不喜歡在這個473奈米的光照的地方
That 473 is purple light
那473是紫色的光
it doesn't like
它不喜歡
so you see it spread out
所以你看它都散開來
it's definitely no accident
這絕對不是偶然
Then Mr. Li Changheng Li told me that
那這個李長恆李老師告訴我說
why ? because they are afraid of death
為什麼?因為他們怕死
He said after you look at the picture for a long time
他說你看照久了之後
the nuclei of these cells
這些細胞的細胞核
shrinking
萎縮的
will die
會死掉
So it is afraid of death, so it spreads out
所以它怕死,所以它就散開來了
so this is very important
所以這個是很重要的
So this light actually, here is another movie
所以這個光事實上,這邊又是一個電影
it puts the light outside on purpose
它把光故意打在外面
Then slowly change this lit area
然後慢慢改變這個打光的區域
Then the cell escapes
然後這個細胞就逃跑
just run away
就逃跑
There is no light here, these are the areas of light
這邊是沒有光的,這些是有光的區域
You see the cells run away from here again
你看到細胞會從這邊又逃跑
That is to say, like Ganyang, you can design a trap
也就是說像感陽一樣,你可以設計一個圈套
Change it up so the cells are like your sheep
把它改改改,所以細胞就像你養的羊一樣
can do whatever you want
可以按照你想要做的事情去做
In addition, it also conducted an experiment
另外它還做了一個實驗
But this doesn't seem to work, the movie won't move
不過這個好像不會工作,這個電影不會動
That is to say, the light here will generate a
就是說這邊這個光會產生一個
From light intensity to light weakness, a T degree
從光強到光弱,一個T度
This cell was originally in this place
這個細胞原來在這個地方
It deliberately hit the body of this cell
它故意打在這個細胞的身上
This cell will quickly escape to this place from here
這個細胞就會從這邊趕快逃到這個地方
Escape to that brightness where it can feel non-life threatening
逃到它可以覺得沒有生命威脅的那個亮度
it just stops
它就停下來
So here is a T degree
所以這邊是有個T度
There is a staircase-like intensity from high to low
就是有一個像樓梯一樣的強度從高到低
After escaping to a certain intensity it can
逃到某一種強度之後它就可以
So from now on, we can know that light actually has a very, very, very, very, very, very very impact on life.
所以從此可以知道說光事實上對生命是非常非常非常有影響的
There is also Chen Bizhang in our India Center
我們印科中心還有一位陳碧璋
Teacher Chen
陳老師
Ms. Chen joined our center in July 2013
陳老師 2013年7月加入我們中心
He specializes in this interesting work called
他專門研究這種一個有趣的工作叫做
3D movies of living cells or biological samples
三維的活的細胞或者是生物的樣品的電影
He said that he specialized in making this kind of film just like making a movie.
他說他就是像拍電影一樣專門拍這種
that his
那他的
The male and female protagonists of the movie are all kinds of biological tissues
拍電影的男主角女主角就是各式各樣的生物組織
when i made a movie
以前拍電影的時候
especially in the microscope filming
尤其在顯微鏡拍電影
The hero and heroine must do something
男主角女主角都必須要做一些處理
Just put some hot pepper on it to fix him
就是塗上一些辣讓他固定
just dead
就是死掉了
can't move
就不能夠動
I can't see clearly when I move
一動就看不清楚
then he is not
那他不是
He developed a new technique that is
他發展一個新的技術是
He can see anything
不管什麼樣的東西他都可以看
And can see more clearly than others
而且可以看得比人家更清楚
alive again
又是活的
Moreover, he can see images from all directions in real time.
而且是即時各個方向的影像他都可以看得到
the most important point
最重要一點
That is to say, the image he saw
就是說他看到的影像
yes
是
this is a formula
這個是一個公式
formula engraved in stone
刻在石頭上的公式
by Professor Abbe
是由德國的阿貝教授
Professor Abbe died in 1905
阿貝教授是在1905年過世的
He is an independent director of Zeiss AG
他在蔡司公司當任獨立董事
Then he wrote down this formula
然後他就寫下這個公式
that is
就是說
Recording is proportional to wavelength
記錄跟波長成正比
Refractive index of the lens used
跟所使用的透鏡的折射率
inversely proportional to the dirty angle of the lens
成反比跟透鏡的髒角
The Sci-C tower is inversely proportional to
的Sci-C塔是成反比
This means that the world knows
這個是指是舉世皆知
color limit
叫做繞色極限
This mainland China is called the limit of color rendering
這中國大陸叫演色極限
It is called Deflection Limit in English
就是英文叫Deflection Limit
That is to say, no matter how you look at it
也就是說你不管怎麼樣去看
see things with an optical microscope
用光學顯微鏡去看事情
basically about half a wavelength of resolution
基本上就是大約半個波長的解析度
This is what everyone knows
這個是大家都知道的
Our Professor Chen Mizhen
我們的陳秘珍教授
He can break through the limit like this
他就可以突破這樣子的極限
Former Yongjian academician he won the Nobel Prize
前永建院士他拿諾貝爾獎
because of the use of fluorescent green protein
就是因為使用螢光綠蛋白
fluorescent green protein
螢光綠蛋白
It's about two nanometers wide
它的大小大概兩個奈米的寬度
Then three nanometers in length
然後三個奈米的長度
A fluorescent molecule like this
這樣子的一個螢光分子
Another focused light spot, a focused light spot is about two to three hundred nanometers
再一個聚焦的光點,一個聚焦光點大概就是兩三百個奈米
Then put a fluorescent molecule in such a small one, about 1/500th of it
然後擺在那麼小的裡面,大概是它的五百分之一的一個螢光分子
Then, if you look at the fluorescent image, this light spot is about 1/500th of the entire cell.
然後就用看螢光影像的話,這一個光點大約是整個細胞的五百分之一
So use such a light spot to look at the fluorescent molecules in a cell
所以用這樣一個光點再去看一個細胞裡面的螢光分子
It can obtain very high-dimensional images, you can take a look
它可以得到非常高的空間的影像,各位可以看一下
This is an image of live feed
這是即時動態的一個影像
If you can see the upper left, if your eyes are good enough
那如果各位可以看到左上方的,如果你的眼睛夠好的話
The purple in the upper left represents the nucleus
左上方的紫色代表是細胞核
Green represents the number of microtubules
綠色代表是微管數
Red represents a stereo
紅色代表是立線體
it is the image of a cell
它是一個細胞的影像
Image of a fluorescent green protein called a cell
叫做細胞的螢光綠蛋白的影像
Using such technology
利用這樣子的技術的話
for different proteins
對不同的蛋白質
Bottom is an image of a mouse neuron
底下是一個老鼠的神經細胞的影像
Both are dead fixed
這兩個都是死掉的固定的
Different colors represent different proteins
不同的顏色就代表說是不同的蛋白質
you can see
你都可以看得到
It is very clear that such different representations
非常清楚這樣子不同的代表
these states of protein
蛋白質的這些狀況
Then you can see the cells
然後可以看得到細胞
Cellular organelles that can be seen inside the cell
可以看到細胞裡面的細胞的細胞器
You can also see protein
還有可以看到蛋白質
You can also see the real-time video like this
也可以看到即時動態的這樣子的影像
Just ask me what he thinks
你就問我說他怎麼看
of course he's amazing
當然他非常了不起
he invented a technique
他發明了一個技術
This technology is the same as in 2014
這個技術是跟2014年
Technology developed with Professor Eric Bezit, Nobel Prize in Chemistry
諾貝爾化學獎 Eric Bezit教授一起發展出來的技術
This technique is the general optical microscope is like this
這個技術就是一般的光學顯微鏡是這樣子的
The objective lens of the microscope is focused on the sample
顯微鏡的物鏡聚焦在樣品上
What about after you look at it like this?
那你這樣看下去之後呢
Because what you look at in front of you and behind you will interfere with you
因為你看的前面的後面的都會干擾你
like during the day, everyone
就像各位白天的時候
Can you see the stars in the sky? Can't you?
看得到天上的星星嗎?看不到嘛
only at night
晚上才會看得到
Because there is no such light pollution at night
因為晚上沒有這些光害啦
Can you see the stars?
才看得到星星嘛
So the stars are always there
所以星星其實永遠都在那邊
just remove the background
只是把背景給除掉
So this background will affect you
所以呢這個前後的背景會影響到你
So generally speaking, use confoco
所以一般來講就用confoco
Confoco focuses the light spot to a very small point
confoco就把光點聚焦到很小的一點
or to photo, multi-photo
或者是to photo,multi-photo
look at this sample
來看這個樣品
Then swipe this sample
然後掃動這個樣品
about ten years ago
在大約十年前
they developed a technique
他們發展出一個技術
That is to say, I don't want to use this light
就是說那我不要打這個光
I light from the side
我從側面打光
If you have this experience
各位如果有這種經驗
Walk into a room and see a light count down
走到一個房間看到一道光數下來
it's full of dust
裡面都是灰塵
That's because you're here to light
那就是因為你是在這邊打光
your eyes can see
你的眼睛看得到
Otherwise, how can you usually see the dust?
否則平常你怎麼會看得到灰塵呢
then this is the concept
那這個就是那個概念
It's just a ray of light
就是一道光打下來
you are in this area of ​​no light
你在這個沒有光的區域
Look at the effect of light and matter
看有光的跟物質作用的
So this can see a lot
所以呢這個可以看到很多
flash some images
閃射的一些影像
that flashing image
那閃射的影像
you can put very small things
就可以把很細微的東西
can show
可以展現出來
that goes further
那更進一步
they were in previous years
他們在前幾年
how about a light like this
把這樣子的一個光呢
so-called back handle
用所謂的背收柄
Then you will ask me what is a back handle
那你就會問我什麼叫做背收柄
Reciprocal square is a fraction of mathematics
背收方形是一個數學的一個含數
What about the production of the back handle?
那背收柄的產生呢
It is the tail of this object
它是用這個物徑的賴尾
Raiwei it puts the light in the light
賴尾它把光進來的光
just become a circle
就是變成一個圈
a ring light
一個環形的光源
After typing in
打進去之後
The ring light will focus
環形光源會聚焦
Interfering with each other after focusing
聚焦之後會互相干涉
interfere with each other
互相干涉就會產生
some interference fringes
一些干涉的條紋
You can see it in the next picture
下張圖可以看得到
It shoots light in, and it shoots light in with two object paths
它把光打進來,用兩個物徑把光打進來
One is light coming in, after the light comes in, the light will interfere with each other
一個是光打進來,打進來之後這個光會互相干涉
As far as two lights are concerned, after interference, interference fringes will be produced one by one.
就兩道光,干涉之後會產生一條一條的干涉條紋
This is the interference fringe, this puts some dye in it
這就是干涉條紋,這放了一些染料進去
You can see these interference fringes one by one
你就可以看到這些干涉條紋一條一條
Then these interference fringes are the same as the focus just now
那這些干涉條紋跟剛剛一般這樣子的聚焦
Gather to a minimum thickness of about 500 microns
聚到最小大概500個micron的厚度
This is about 0.5micron thick
這個大概0.5micron的厚度
Sorry for my mistake, this is about 5micron in thickness
對不起我說錯,這個是大概5micron的厚度
This is the thickness of 0.5micron, one-tenth of the thickness
這個是0.5micron的厚度,十分之一的厚度
so it can look thin
所以它可以看得很薄
Then do a tomographic scan, just like this
然後就做斷層掃描一樣,就這樣掃
A living one like this, this is a living IC package
這樣子的一個活的,這是一個活體的IC包
it just sweeps over
它就這樣掃過去
We went to see the video, he recorded it
我們去看到的影像,他就把它記錄下來
After recording it, he reconstructed it from measurements
記錄下來之後呢,他從三圍去重建
Different directions to rebuild, like this
不同的方向去重建,這樣子的
Here's the actual architecture of his experiment
這是他的實驗的實際上的架構
Two object paths, actually there are three object paths here
兩個物徑,其實這邊有三個物徑
There are actually
這邊其實還有
As you can see, this is a
那可以看到,這是一個
cancer cell
癌細胞
It's a real-time motion image, a fluorescent image
它是即時動態的影像,螢光的影像
the background looks very dark
背景看起來非常的黑暗
so it looks very clear
所以看起來非常明
The contrast is very good
這個contrast對比度非常好
images like this
像這樣子的影像
he did a lot
他做了非常的多
I can't report to everyone one by one.
我不能夠一一的跟各位做報告
Because it involves a lot of research
因為這裡面牽涉到研究很多
basic biology, and some
基本的生物學,還有一些
pharmacology, and some other reactions
藥物學,還有一些其他的一些反應
Then I have selected a few to compare
那我已經選擇了幾個比較
simple
簡單的
You can see this at the bottom left
這個左下方各位可以看到的
The first one is an image of the nucleus
第一個這是核的影像
The second is the image of this solid
第二個是這個立線體的影像
It is the image of generating ATP to generate energy
就是產生ATP產生能量的影像
This is the same cell
這是一個同樣一個細胞
And this is the image of the inner fat network
然後這個是內脂網的影像
That is, it can distinguish between different proteins
也就是說它可以分辨不同的蛋白質
Individual images can then be extracted
然後可以把個別的影像抽離出來
and put it together like this
然後再組合在一起像這樣子
Then it places different slices at different depths
然後它在不同的深度不同的切片的地方
it can see its
它可以看到它的
instant dynamic response
即時動態的反應
different location
不同的位置
So put it all together and you can see the change of its overall image
所以把它全部都組合在一起可以看到它整體的影像的變化
this is
這個是
one depends on the present
一個仰賴目前
very important
非常重要的
The development of optical technology
光學的技術的發展
And computer big data processing
還有電腦大數據的處理
And there is the image
還有就是影像
Some techniques for rebuilding
重建的一些技術
can see very important
可以看到非常重要的
This is a T cell
這是一個T細胞
After he found a foreign cell
他發現外來的一個細胞之後
he opened his mouth
他就張開了口
then swallow it
然後就把它吞死掉
This is an image showing no foreign cells seen
這是顯示沒有看到外來細胞的影像
just see it
只看到它
Then you can see the mouth open
然後你可以看到這個口張開來
then he swallowed it
然後他把它給吞死掉
Some movies of some important some cells like this
像這樣子一些重要的一些細胞的一些電影
is his specialty
是他的專業
This is just in the T cell
這個是剛剛在T細胞
when you want to open your mouth to swallow it
要張口吞死它的時候
When he opens his mouth, some acidic substances will be produced
他口張開來會有一些酸性的物質產生
then lyse the cells
然後溶解掉細胞
swallow it up
把它吞死進去
This word is the same cell
這個的話是同一個細胞
look at it from different directions
不同的方向來看它
So you can see that this cell divides in the middle
那各位可以看到這個細胞分裂在中間
Then split successfully
然後就分裂成功
and then become two different individuals
然後變成兩個不同的個體
That
那
This is a kind of Hila-Sel, which is the kind of cancer cells of uterine well cancer
這個的話是一個那種Hila-Sel,就是那種子宮井癌的癌症細胞
It has no way to successfully split in the process of splitting, entangled together
它在分裂的過程中沒有辦法成功的分裂,糾纏在一起
That is, the cells have no ability to regenerate.
那就是這個細胞其實已經沒有再生的能力了
That is, after it is treated with drugs, it will not regenerate, it will only wither
就是它受到藥物的處理之後,它就不會再生了,它只有凋零了
So some images like this can be seen by it
所以這樣子的一些影像都可以被它看到
that's a fruit camp one...sorry, it's a live insect egg
那這是一個果營的一個...對不起,這是一個現蟲的卵
This is the egg of a living insect, the green one you see now is its chromosome
這是一個現蟲的卵,各位看到的現在綠色的這個是它的染色體
it is undergoing nuclear division of this cell
它正在進行這個細胞的核分裂
So the following is the fruit camp
所以下面這個才是果營
This is the egg of the fruit camp
這是果營的卵
Sure enough, the soft cell membrane
果然的軟的細胞膜
you can see
各位可以看到
it's been squeezing each other
它是一直在互相擠壓
How does its extruding cells extrude and harden?
它的擠壓的細胞擠壓的硬力跟硬變如何產生的
In fact it has always been a puzzle
事實上一直是一個謎題
How do these mechanical effects arise
這些機械作用是如何產生
In fact it is not clear
事實上並不清楚
This is the first time you can see so clearly
這是第一次可以看到那麼清楚
A change like this on its cell membrane
它的細胞膜上面的這樣子的一個變化
This is the heart of a zebrafish three-day-old baby zebrafish
這是一個斑馬魚三天大的小斑馬魚的心臟
The heart of this zebrafish
這個斑馬魚的心臟
You can see that is to say
各位可以看到就是說
about this size
大約這個尺寸
About 50 to 100micron heart
大約是50到100micron的心臟
Then it also moves with the cardiomyocytes
然後它還隨著在心肌細胞在動
The orange part represents the nucleus
橘色的部分代表是細胞核
The green part is the cytoplasm
綠色的部分是細胞質
So you can clearly see
所以各位可以很清楚的看到
entire
整個
From cell to heart
從細胞到心臟
and then what else
然後另外呢
This is a mouse brain neuron
這個是老鼠的腦神經細胞
this is the nucleus
這個是細胞核
Then this branch is the nerve cell's
然後這個分支是這種神經細胞的
one by one nerve
一支一支的神經
Then he can see clearly
那他也可以看得很清楚
Of course this is processed
那當然這是經過處理
After transparent processing
透明化的處理之後
This is before processing, this is after processing
這是處理前,這是處理後
Then you can see the brain cells go deep inside some of the
然後就可以看到腦細胞深入裡面的一些
The last one you can see is
最後一張各位可以看到就是
his technique
他的技術
Fluorescence Microscopy
螢光顯微技術
so-called
用這樣子所謂的
Sad disease like this tomographic technique
悲傷病的這樣子的斷層掃描的技術
actually very very important
事實上非常非常重要
His Science of Paper last year
他去年的Science of Paper
Selected as one of the Science for a whole year
被選為是Science一整年裡面
most important articles
最重要的文章
Then he gets Science
然後他獲得Science
there is a very important
有一個很重要的
It's called the Newcombe Cleveland Award
叫做Newcombe Cleveland Award
This award has been around for more than eighty years
這個 award 已經八十幾年了
Eighty years ago it was Newcombe Cleveland
在八十幾年前是Newcombe Cleveland
Their family donated a sum of money
他們這個family捐了一筆錢
eighty years ago
在八十幾年前
His prize money is one thousand dollars
他的獎金金額是一千元美金
Eighty years ago, one thousand yuan was a lot
八十幾年前的一千元很大
So there was a
所以當時有一個叫做
Soulland dollars award
Soulland dollars award
is the highest award
就是最高的獎項
It is the highest award of AAAS in the United States and Science magazine
是美國AAAS 也是Science雜誌最高的一個獎項
So in February this year, during the Lunar New Year
所以他今年二月 農曆春節的時候
Everyone celebrates the New Year here and he flew to New York to receive the award
大家在這邊過年他飛到紐約去領獎
We had a lot of bad news in the hospital
我們當時因為院內很多不好的消息
So the good news was never reported.
所以也都沒有報導這件好消息
OK good
OK 好
The remaining time is now eight nineteen
剩下的時間 現在八點十九分
not much time left
剩下的時間不多
Then I will report to you
那我就再跟各位報告
something else
還有一些什麼東西
it's more interesting
是比較有趣的事情
In fact, there are many interesting things
其實有趣的事情很多
I have limited time to share
我能夠分享的時間有限
My personal knowledge is also limited
我個人的學問也有限
So I thought I'd make some comparisons
所以我想我就講一些比較
interesting things i find
我覺得有趣的事情
Because a reporter came to me and asked me
因為有記者就跑來問我說
The invisibility cloak is not a dream
隱形斗篷不是夢
that Berkeley professor
那個伯克萊障強教授
it was last september
這是去年的9月
Many major newspapers in Taiwan published it
這個台灣的很多大報都登出來
say this
說這個
the most important thing is to say
最重要的就是說
Ask Zhang Xiang if this invisibility cloak is real
問張翔說這個隱形斗篷是真的嗎
Professor Zhang Xiang said I can't see any obstacles
張翔教授說我看不到任何障礙
Many people came to me and asked
很多人就跑來問我說
Isn't that what you do?
你不是就是做這個的嗎
what is that obstacle
那障礙到底是什麼
why can't i see
為什麼看不到
this is a joke
這個是一個笑話
because of the invisibility cloak
因為有隱形斗篷
so can't see
所以就看不到
This is actually a very important development
這個事實上是很重要的一個發展
How to tell this story?
這個故事怎麼講呢?
That is to say, Professor Zhang Qiang published this Size Paper last year
就是說張強教授他在去年發表了這一篇Size Paper
Then this Size Paper will tell you
那這篇Size Paper就告訴你說
Suppose you make some special artificial structures on a surface
假設你在一個表面上面去做一些特殊的人工結構
These artificial structures allow incoming light
這些人工結構可以讓進來的光
Follow your ideas to the direction you want him to go
按照你的想法走到你想要他走的方向
that's all
就是這樣子而已
So what if I make an invisibility cloak
所以呢 我如果做一個隱形斗篷
It's easy for you to lose sight of me
要讓你看不見我 很容易
I just let the light in
我就是讓光進來
Then run to the back
然後呢 就跑到背後去
you can't see me
你就看不到我
Then the light went to the back and that's it
然後光就走到後面去了 就這樣子
So what about his experiment?
所以他的實驗呢
That is to say that on a surface with bumps and bumps
就是證明說 在一個有凹凹凸凸的表面上
I went to lay out a lot of structures that are resistant to you
我去佈置了很多耐你的結構
make him look flat
讓他看起來是平的
This is what his experiment looks like
他的實驗就是這樣子
So it turns out that this is where RO stands out
所以也就是說原來這是RO突出的地方
looks wrinkled
看起來會變成很多皺紋
but i'm up there now
可是我現在在上面
put some nanostructures
擺一些奈米結構
it looks flat to me
我看起來它很平整
it is flat
它是平的
that's it
就是這樣子
So this concept is very important
所以這個概念非常重要
So if you ask me
那如果各位問我說
There are various versions of this story
這個故事有各種版本
I won't talk much
我就不多講
Size's cover is an invisibility cloak
Size的封面就是做隱形斗篷
then very important
然後非常重要
I still want to tell this story a little bit.
那這個故事我還是要稍微講一下
The story develops over a period of time
這個故事發展有一段時間
about 10 years
大概有10年
That is to say, 10 years ago, some people proposed that
也就是說10年前就有一些人提出來說
Matter is made up of atoms and molecules
物質是原子分子所組成的
Assuming that humans can make artificial atoms and molecules
假設人類可以做人造的原子跟分子
to form a substance
就可以組成一種物質
called
叫做
Metal material, Metal means
Metal material,Metal的意思就是
Walking up means above, beyond
行而上,就是above,beyond的意思
So human technology
所以人類的技術
Nanotechnology has developed to the present
奈米技術發展到現在
materials that can be made
所能夠做出來的這樣的材料
Because artificial atoms have to have structure
因為人工原子要有結構
So these artificial atoms and the size of the molecule
所以這些人工原子跟分子它的大小
Can't be as small as an atom
也不能夠像原子那麼小
Because its most basic composition is the atomic molecule
因為它最基本的組成還是原子分子
Right, so it's always slightly bigger than an atomic molecule
對不對,所以它始終要比原子分子稍微大一點
But it must be more visible than us humans
但是又必須要比我們人類可見光
The wavelength that can be seen like this comes from a small
可以看到的這樣子的波長來得小
to do something interesting
才有辦法做一些有趣的事情
So a structure like this
所以這樣子的一種結構
It affects physical properties that humans care about
它會影響到人類會在乎的物理性質
Basically the two coefficients of electricity and magnetism
基本上就是電跟磁兩個係數
The two coefficients of electricity and magnetism
那這兩個電跟磁的係數
natural material
天然的材料
Its electric and magnetic coefficients are composed of atoms and molecules
它的電跟磁的係數有原子分子所組成
Influence
影響
The physical properties of electricity and magnetism in artificial structures
人工結構它的電跟磁的物理性質
are influenced by these artificial small structures
是由這些人工的小的結構所影響
To have an impact you have to put what comes in
要有影響你就要把進來的東西
Changes in what is measured will have an impact
量測的東西去改變才會有影響
otherwise it won't work
要不然就沒有作用
right
對不對
So these things you have to go through a special design
所以這些東西你就要經過特別的設計
So at that time, many people jumped in to do such an experiment.
所以當時就很多人就一頭栽進去做這樣的實驗
Including materials responsible for setting up
包括負責設的材料
is everything before
就是以前所有的事情
This is how light goes
光都是這樣走的
Refractive index
折射率
it goes the other way
它走另外一邊
Then everyone used to walk on the right
然後以前所有的人都是靠右邊走
it keeps to the left
它靠左邊走
that anyway
那anyway
something like it
它這樣子的東西
But later found a difficulty
但是後來發現到有一個困難
That is, if it's really efficient
就是說如果它真的很有效率的話
that comes in quickly
那進來的東西很快就
If you want to have an effect with him, after it has an effect, the ones behind will have no effect with him.
要跟他產生作用,產生作用之後在後面的就跟他沒有作用
Because everything was done by his predecessor
因為全部都被他前任作用完了
So after a few years, ten years
所以經過了幾年、十年之後
Started with some smart ones like
開始有一些聰明的人,像
CAPASO, Professor, Department of Applied Physics, Harvard University
CAPASO,哈佛大學應用物理系的教授
He said, let's not work so hard
他就說,我們不要做那麼辛苦
Because making that Metameteria requires artificial atoms and artificial molecules
因為做那個Metameteria要做人工原子、人工分子
To do it well, one by one, to do it well for many years
要做好後,那一顆一顆做,要做好多年
So we just make a thin layer
所以我們就做薄薄一層就好了
Anyway, only the first few layers work.
反正也就只有前面那幾層有作用
So it's called Metameteria Surface
所以就叫做Metameteria Surface
We focus on Metameteria Surface
我們專心做Metameteria Surface
Metameteria Surface as long as the efficiency is good enough
Metameteria Surface只要效率夠好的話
Soon you can complete the artificial substance you want
很快就可以完成你想像要的人工物質
So he proposed to use this V-shaped
所以他就提出用這種V型
Nanostructures of something like a boomerang
像迴力標一樣的東西的奈米結構
To control the electromagnetic wave or light that enters the color
來控制入色的電磁波或者是光
It hits this entry above each dot
它打在每一個點上面的這個項位
After it interacts with it, it will produce different items
就它跟它作用之後會產生不同的項位
ok, i'm sorry, there's no way to not give the formula at all
好,我很抱歉,沒有辦法完全不給公式
So let me talk about
所以我大概講一下
When you were in junior high school, you learned that entering the character role is equal to the anti-role role
各位在國中的時候有學過入色角等於反色角
Snees Law, Snees Law
折色定律,Snees Law
N1, Sci-Ct-1 is equal to N2, Sci-Ct-2
N1,Sci-Ct-1等於N2,Sci-Ct-2
So look at the fish in the water in the air
所以空氣中看水中的魚
The position of the fish will be different from its real position
魚的位置跟它真實的位置會不一樣
Because of the folding angle
因為折色角的關係
Because water has a different refractive index than air, right?
因為水跟空氣的折色率不一樣,對不對
that description is correct
那樣子的形容是正確的
But that water has to be pretty flat
但是那個水面必須是非常平的
If the water surface is uneven, if the interface is uneven
如果水面不平,如果這個界面是不平的
is a structured word
是有結構的話
It is necessary to put the contribution of this structure in
就要把這個結構的貢獻放進去
so without it
所以就因為沒它
So capasso wrote the so-called generized snare's law
所以capasso就寫了所謂的generized snare's law
Generalized, extensive snare's law
廣義的、廣泛的snare's law
That is to say, one more contribution is the contribution generated by the surface
也就是說多了一項貢獻是由表面產生的貢獻
There is one more item from reflection or refraction.
就多了這一項從反射或者是折射都多了一項
This is one more item, he won the highest award of the International Society for Conceptual Engineering
就多了這一項他拿到了國際觀念工程學會最高的獎項
The Optical Society of America's highest award
美國光學學會最高的獎項
And iQIPOE's highest award
還有iQIPOE最高的獎項
It's because of this extra item
就是因為多了這一項
so very important
所以很重要
Ask me if it's simple, very simple
問我簡不簡單非常簡單
but he just wrote it out
但是他就是把它寫出來
With this concept
有了這個概念之後
Many people do related research
很多的人就做相關的研究
We also did some research
我們也做了一些研究
What we do is the so-called full photo
我們做的是所謂的全相片
General full photo like your credit card
一般的全相片像你的信用卡
Or those full photos that you see at art museums
或者是各位去藝術博物館看到的那些全相片
We are in every pixel of every full photo
我們在每一個全相片的每一個pixel裡面
This is a single pixel
這是一個單一的pixel
Put different nanostructures inside
裡面再放不同的奈米的結構
the nanostructure
這個奈米結構
One is NTU, the other is RCAAS
一個是NTU,一個是RCAAS
Then it goes in a different direction
然後它的方向不一樣
If the direction is different
方向不一樣的話
The images you get in and out with different polarized light are different.
你不同偏正的光照進去出來的影像就是不一樣的
then you ask me
那你問我說
what's the fun in that
那這有什麼好玩
that is to tell you
那就是告訴你說
In fact, the previous polarized full photo
事實上以前的偏正全相片
Only one image can be projected
都只能夠投一個影像
There is no biased information in that image.
那那個影像裡面是沒有偏正的訊息的
We can now be inside a pixel
我們現在可以在一個pixel裡面
also contains biased messages
還包含了偏正的訊息
That is to say, the original image
也就是說原來的那個影像
it is intensity
它是強度,intensity
also in different colors
還有不同的顏色
There are different information
還有不同的這些information
So we now add one more dimension
那我們現在又再多加了一個維度
It is an additional dimension of information
就是一個額外的一個information的維度
Then you ask me, can I add more?
那你問我說還可以多加其他的嗎
sure
當然可以
if you have the ability
你如果有本事
It will change from three-dimensional to four-dimensional to five-dimensional to multi-dimensional
它會從三維的變四維的變五維的變多維的
Multidimensional information is placed in a Single Pixel
Multidimensional的information擺在一個Single Pixel
As long as you can design some nanostructures like this
只要你能夠設計出一些奈米的結構在這樣子
so you can control
所以你就可以控制
Is it projected to be NTU or projected to be RCA
它投影出來是NTU還是投影出來是RCA
It can also project on both sides simultaneously
它也可以同時兩邊投影
It has something to do with the polarized direction of your colored light
跟你入色光的偏正方向有關係
that this is very interesting stuff
那這個是非常有趣的東西
Then after we develop these things
那我們發展了這些東西之後
That's because it's targeting a wavelength
那因為它是針對一個波長
Later we also developed RGB
後來我們也發展RGB
Different wavelengths are broadband
就不同的波長就是寬頻的
Full Spectrum Different Colors
全光譜不同顏色
All can be applied to a full photo of a nanometer like this
都可以適用這樣子的一個奈米的全相片
Then this is the result of it
那這個都是它的結果
Then you ask me, what is the use of having these things?
那你問我說,有這些東西有什麼用?
Of course useful
當然有用
You may not know
各位可能不知道
about fifty or sixty years ago
在大約五六十年前
After the Second and Fourth Four Seasons War
二四四季大戰結束之後
A very famous large pharmaceutical company in Europe
歐洲的一個非常有名的大藥廠
when it is making a medicine
它在做一個藥的時候
Everyone knows that medicine is
大家都知道做藥就是
After knowing that a certain molecule is useful
知道某一個分子有用之後
just synthesize it
就去合成它
But during the synthesis
但是合成的過程中
that molecular weight is the same
那個分子量是一樣的
but it is mirrored
但是它是有鏡像的
its two mirror images
它兩個鏡像
Those two mirror images are just right
那這兩個鏡像剛剛好
this left hand
這個左手
this kind
這種
Right hand
Right hand
open me
開我跟
This one is Left hand
這個一個是Left hand
one is sorry
一個是對不起
One is Right hand
一個是Right hand
One is Left hand
一個是Left hand
Then what
然後呢
Just right for its medicinal properties
剛剛好它的藥性
Chemical properties are different
化學藥性是不一樣的
so what
所以呢
There are many of these
有很多的這種
After the sick woman took the medicine
病婦吃了這個藥之後
Babies born without hands
生出來的小孩子就沒有了手
no hands
就沒有了手
Well, this matter was actually not settled until the lawsuit was settled three years ago.
那這件事情其實到三年前官司才settle
A total of nearly 5 million pounds of this money was paid to these victims
一共賠了大概將近500多萬磅的這個錢給這些受害者
and the victims who are still alive
還有還活著的受害者
What about the drug Salidome?
那這個沙利豆麥這個藥
This drug was actually a very important drug in the past
這個藥事實上以前是一個非常重要的藥
That is because in the process of treatment
那就是因為治藥的過程中
Neglected that the medicinal properties of the left hand and the right hand are different
疏忽了這個左手跟右手的藥性是不一樣的
Hence the aftermath
所以就產生了這樣的後遺症
Then you ask me how do you detect the left hand and right hand
那你問我說那你怎麼去偵測這個左手跟右手
that's really troublesome
那真的很麻煩
Your change means that you want to synthesize this medicine after
你這個變成是說你要把這個合成的藥之後
to separate it
要把它分開來
how do you detect
那你要怎麼偵測
Even if you take it apart today
就算你今天把它分開來
do you worry
你會不會擔心
Then you will say that I will melt it in the water
那你就會說那我就把它融在水裡面
and then use
然後再用
This different left-handed off right-handed off to hit it
這個不同的左旋關右旋關去打它
Then look out the result
然後看出來的結果
But the results you see need a lot of molecules to have an effect
但是你看出來的結果要很多分子才會有影響
So is there any way to detect instantly
所以有沒有什麼方法可以立即即時的檢測
Left Hand circular police and Y hand circular police came out
出來的Lefthand circular polise跟Y hand circular polise
You can go to different points by typing it out
打出來可以到不同的點
Because we use Laimi's technology
因為我們用賴米的技術
So we can have a very small range
所以我們可以很小的範圍
We can do something like this with very little
很少量的東西我們就可以去做這樣的事情
So we can do a very efficient
所以我們可以做一個很有效率
and very fast filtering
而且很快速的篩選
Just to do a meta analyzer like this
就是去做這樣子的一個meta analyzer
It is the use of this meta surface technology to do the meta analyzer just mentioned
就是剛剛講的用這種meta surface的技術去做meta analyzer
This article was recently accepted for publication
這個文章是最近才剛剛被接受發表
So with this structure of Laimi in different directions
所以用這種賴米的這種結構不同的方向
Different bias control
不同的偏正控制
Polarized in a different direction, since it is found that it will project onto this point
不同的方向偏振,因為發現到它會投影到這一點
or projected to this point, depending on its polarization
或是投影到這一點,取決於它的偏振
Then its polarization is after interacting with this substance
那它偏振就是跟這個物質作用之後
what does its polarization look like
它的偏振是什麼樣子
ok, then this me
好,那這個我
What about our students, so
我們的學生呢,因此呢
Just taught by Carposo
就被Carposo教授呢
Project Maxima, recruited to his laboratory
千里馬計畫,招去他的實驗室
Then he is in this year's
那他在今年的這個
June 3 cover
6月3號封面
Just made a Metal Lens
就做了一個Metal Lens
that is a lens
那就是一個透鏡
Because all photos are very complicated, an image needs to be projected
因為全相片都很複雜,要投一個影像
Then when he went, he said, what are you doing?
然後去的時候他說,你做什麼?
Do Metal Hologram
做Metal Hologram
You say Metal Hologram, don't bother
你說Metal Hologram,不要那麼麻煩
Just project on a point
只要投影在一個點上就好
So before projecting as an image
所以以前要投影成一個影像
Projected at a point, it is called Metal Lens
投影在一個點,那就叫Metal Lens
So now this student is called Chen Weiting
所以現在這個學生叫陳維廷
he did very well
他做得非常好
Then this year he published an article
那今年他就出了一篇
Size Fondant, called Metal Lens
Size Fondant,叫Metal Lens
Then, take the H of Harvard
然後呢,把哈佛的H就可以
see clearly
看得很清楚
And now he is helping Apple, Google and the three sacred companies every day
然後他現在天天都在幫忙做給Apple, Google還有神聖三個公司
Because they all signed him up to buy the technology
因為他們都跟他簽約去買這個技術
To replace what? To replace the lens of this phone
要取代什麼呢?要取代這個手機的鏡頭
So the last few slides
所以最後幾張投影片
That is to say, from the past, human beings invented
就是說各位從過去人類發明
Various nanostructures
各式各樣的奈米的結構
then through conversion optics
然後經過轉換光學
Can make this raised thing look like it's not raised
可以把這個凸起來的東西看起來不是凸起來的
just pretending to be flat
就是偽裝成是平的
Then you can make adjustments
然後可以去做調節的
convertible
可以轉換的
To the so-called Meta Device
到所謂的Meta Device
That is, many devices or components in the future
就是未來很多的裝置或者是元件
Just use it directly, it is done in this nano way
就是用直接它是用這種奈米的方式來做
will be
將會是
We consider a very important development in optics
我們認為在光學的一個非常重要的一個發展
The reason is because optics is a science that controls the path of light
原因因為光學就是控制光行徑的一個學問
Or a study of the interaction between light and matter
或者是研究光跟物質作用的一個學問
Finally, I want to show you a video
最後要秀給各位看一個影片
Because many reporters asked me
因為很多記者問我說
How do you feel about what Professor Zhang made?
那想張教授做的東西你有什麼感覺
I dare not speak because I respect Professor Zhang very much
我都不敢講話因為我非常尊敬張教授
He is the chairman of our middle academic information committee
他是我們中間學術資訊委員會的主席
I worked for three years
做了三年我任內
Then I thought of a solution
我後來就想到一個 solution
I found this slide
我就找到這張投影片
This slideshow is made by me
這張投影片是我做的
I went out of my way to find this movie
我特地去找這個電影
use your skin to change color and texture.
use your skin to change color and texture.
There's some algae in the foreground and an octopus.
There's some algae in the foreground and an octopus.
Isn't that amazing?
Isn't that amazing?
Now Roger spooked him so he took off with a cloud of ink,
Now Roger spooked him so he took off with a cloud of ink,
lands, and when he lands the octopus says,
lands, and when he lands the octopus says,
I've been seen best thing to do is get as big as I can get.
I've been seen best thing to do is get as big as I can get.
That big brown makes his eye spot very big.
That big brown makes his eye spot very big.
So he's bluffing, let's do it backwards.
So he's bluffing, let's do it backwards.
I thought he was joking when he first showed it,
I thought he was joking when he first showed it,
I thought it was all graphics.
I thought it was all graphics.
So here it is in reverse.
So here it is in reverse.
Watch the skin color, watch the skin texture,
Watch the skin color, watch the skin texture,
just an amazing animal can change color and texture
just an amazing animal can change color and texture
to match the surroundings.
to match the surroundings.
Watch them blend right into this algae.
Watch them blend right into this algae.
One, two, three.
One, two, three.
Now he's gone and so am I.
Now he's gone and so am I.
Pattern, color, whiteness, and texture.
Pattern, color, whiteness, and texture.
Actually I have many, many videos
其實我有很多很多影片
I just choose one
我只是選其中一個
That Zhang Yu, you dropped him out of the sea
那個張宇你把他從海裡面掉上來
As soon as he arrives at the fake version, his eyes will see the color of your fake version
一到假版他眼睛就看到你的假版的顏色
His color is exactly the same as the counterfeit color
他的顏色就跟假版顏色完全一樣
change in seconds
在幾秒鐘就變掉
he changes the color
他把顏色改變
how does that color change
那個顏色怎麼改變
Did you say pigment? Not quite
你說是色素嗎?不完全
including his wrinkles
包括他的皺摺
including the structures above the skin
包括皮膚上面的這些結構
his eyes are ring shaped
他眼睛是環形的
his circular vision
他環形的視野
After taking the photo, he will fully blend in with the situation around him.
照完之後他就會跟他四周圍的情境完全融入
So I can tell you about this
所以這件事情就可以跟各位講
In fact, this world already has such
其實這個世界上老早就已經有這種
tunable, adjustable
tunable的、可調節的
reconfigurable, reconfigurable
reconfigurable、重新組合的
Some creatures like this exist
這樣子的一些生物存在
Then why can't there be man-made
那為什麼不可以有人造的
Such a structure exists
這樣子的結構存在
Sure, just say how much it will cost you
當然可以 只是說你要花多少的代價
So I answered the reporter and said
所以我就回答那個記者說
An invisibility cloak I know I'm hard at work 100micron by 100micron
一個隱形斗篷 我知道我做100micron乘100micron很辛苦
An invisibility cloak, say 1 meter by 1 meter
一個隱形斗篷 如果說是1公尺乘1公尺的話
It might take me 1000 times the paper to finish
我可能要花1000倍紙才做得完
With current time and technology
以目前的時間跟技術
But you said it's possible, of course it's possible
但是你說有沒有可能 當然有可能
The world's most famous Southampton UK
世界上最有名的Southampton英國
The University of Southampton is the most famous school in optoelectronics in the world
南安普敦大學是全世界光電最有名的學校
They published the so-called Tunable
他們發表的所謂Tunable的
Some structures like this have been published
這樣子的一些結構已經發表出來了
And there is Professor Hedge in Germany
還有就是在德國Hedge教授
They have also developed a variety of mechanical or electronically controlled
他們也發展出來各種機械式或者是電控的
or thermodynamic heat induction
或者是熱力學熱感應的
Our laboratory has also done some
我們實驗室也做了一些
People are doing Pingtang
人家都是做平堂的
The area of ​​Pingtang is very high
平堂的面積就很高